<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.185"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.185"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.185/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.185/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.185/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.185/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_16_185">
        <num>RCW 82.16.185</num>
        <heading>Credit—State energy performance standard—Early adoption incentive program. (Expires June 30, 2032.)</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the requirements of this section, a light and power business or a gas distribution business is allowed a credit against taxes due under this chapter in an amount equal to:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Incentive payments made in any calendar year under RCW
19.27A.220
; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Documented administrative cost not to exceed eight percent of the incentive payments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The credit must be taken in a form and manner as required by the department.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Credit must be claimed against taxes due under this chapter for the incentive payments made and administrative expenses incurred. Credit earned in one calendar year may not be carried backward but may be claimed against taxes due under this chapter during the same calendar year and for the following two calendar years. The credit may not exceed the tax that would otherwise be due under this chapter. Refunds may not be granted in the place of a credit.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_3__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, any business that has claimed credit in excess of the amount of credit the business earned under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section must repay the amount of tax against which the excess credit was claimed.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department must assess interest on the taxes due under this subsection. Interest must be assessed at the rate provided for delinquent excise taxes under chapter
82.32
RCW, retroactively to the date the credit was claimed, and accrues until the taxes against which the credit was claimed are repaid. The department must provide written notice of the amount due under this subsection and that the amount due must be paid within thirty days of the date of the notice. The department may not impose penalties as provided in chapter
82.32
RCW on taxes due under this subsection unless the amount due is not paid in full by the due date in the notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A business is not liable for excess credits claimed in reliance on amounts reported to the business by the department of commerce as due and payable as provided under RCW
19.27A.220
, if such amounts are later found to be abnormal or inaccurate due to no fault of the business.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of credit taken under this section and the identity of a business that takes the credit is not confidential taxpayer information under RCW
82.32.330
and is subject to disclosure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section expires June 30, 2032.
[
2019 c 285 s 8
.]
NOTES:
Tax preference performance statement
—
2019 c 285 s 8:
&quot;This section is the tax preference performance statement for the tax preference contained in section 8, chapter 285, Laws of 2019. This performance statement is only intended to be used for subsequent evaluation of the tax preference. It is not intended to create a private right of action by any party or be used to determine eligibility for preferential tax treatment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature categorizes this tax preference as one intended to induce implementation of building energy efficiency measures, as indicated in RCW
19.27A.220
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is the legislature's specific public policy objective to increase energy efficiency and the use of renewable fuels that reduce the amount of greenhouse gas emissions in Washington. It is the legislature's intent to provide a credit against the taxes owing by utilities under chapter
82.16
RCW for the incentives provided for the implementation by eligible building owners of energy efficiency and renewable energy measures.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a review finds that measurable energy savings have increased in covered commercial buildings for which building owners are receiving an incentive payment from a qualifying utility, then the legislature intends to extend the expiration date of the tax preference.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In order to obtain the data necessary to perform the review in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_185__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, the joint legislative audit and review committee may refer to the number of building owners receiving an incentive payment from qualifying utilities taking the public utility tax preference under RCW
82.16.185
, the amount of the incentive payment, and the energy use intensity reduction of the buildings as a result of the incentive program, as reported by the department of commerce.&quot; [
2019 c 285 s 7
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
