<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.46.501"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.46.501"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.46.501/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.46.501/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.46.501/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.46.501/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_46_501">
        <num>RCW 74.46.501</num>
        <heading>Average case mix indexes determined quarterly—Facility average case mix index—Medicaid average case mix index</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>From individual case mix weights for the applicable quarter, the department shall determine two average case mix indexes for each medicaid nursing facility, one for all residents in the facility, known as the facility average case mix index, and one for medicaid residents, known as the medicaid average case mix index.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In calculating a facility's two average case mix indexes for each quarter, the department shall include all residents or medicaid residents, as applicable, who were physically in the facility during the quarter in question based on the resident assessment instrument completed by the facility and the requirements and limitations for the instrument's completion and transmission (January 1st through March 31st, April 1st through June 30th, July 1st through September 30th, or October 1st through December 31st).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The facility average case mix index shall exclude all default cases as defined in this chapter. However, the medicaid average case mix index shall include all default cases.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Both the facility average and the medicaid average case mix indexes shall be determined by multiplying the case mix weight of each resident, or each medicaid resident, as applicable, by the number of days, as defined in this section and as applicable, the resident was at each particular case mix classification or group, and then averaging.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In determining the number of days a resident is classified into a particular case mix group, the department shall determine a start date for calculating case mix grouping periods as specified by rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cut-off date for the department to use resident assessment data, for the purposes of calculating both the facility average and the medicaid average case mix indexes, and for establishing and updating a facility's direct care component rate, shall be one month and one day after the end of the quarter for which the resident assessment data applies.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Although the facility average and the medicaid average case mix indexes shall both be calculated quarterly, the cost-rebasing period facility average case mix index will be used throughout the applicable cost-rebasing period in combination with cost report data as specified by RCW
74.46.561
, to establish a facility's allowable cost per case mix unit. A facility's medicaid average case mix index shall be used to update a nursing facility's direct care component rate semiannually.
[
2024 c 246 s 4
;
2021 c 334 s 992
;
2016 c 131 s 5
;
2015 2nd sp.s. c 2 s 2
;
2013 2nd sp.s. c 3 s 2
;
2011 1st sp.s. c 7 s 6
;
2010 1st sp.s. c 34 s 11
;
2006 c 258 s 5
;
2001 1st sp.s. c 8 s 9
;
1998 c 322 s 24
.]
NOTES:
Conflict with federal requirements
—
Effective date
—
2021 c 334:
See notes following RCW
43.79.555
.
Effective date
—
2015 2nd sp.s. c 2:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2015 2nd sp.s. c 2 s 10
.]
Comparative analysis
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 3:
&quot;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For fiscal years 2014 and 2015 and subject to appropriation, the department of social and health services shall do a comparative analysis of the facility-based payment rates calculated on July 1, 2013, using the payment methodology defined in chapter
74.46
RCW, to the facility-based payment rates in effect June 30, 2010. If the facility-based payment rate calculated on July 1, 2013, is smaller than the facility-based payment rate on June 30, 2010, the difference shall be provided to the individual nursing facilities as an add-on payment per medicaid resident day.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>During the comparative analysis performed in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, if it is found that the direct care rate for any facility calculated under chapter
74.46
RCW is greater than the direct care rate in effect on June 30, 2010, then the facility shall receive a ten percent direct care rate add-on to compensate that facility for taking on more acute clients than they have in the past.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rate add-ons provided in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_46_501__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section are subject to the reconciliation and settlement process provided in RCW
74.46.022</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
