<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.260"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.260"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.260/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.260/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.260/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.260/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_04_260">
        <num>RCW 82.04.260</num>
        <heading>Tax on manufacturers and processors of various foods and by-products—Research and development organizations—Travel agents—Certain international activities—Stevedoring and associated activities—Low-level waste disposers—Insurance producers, surplus line brokers, and title insurance agents—Hospitals—Commercial airplane activities—Timber product activities—Canned salmon processors. (&lt;i&gt;Effective until January 1, 2026.&lt;/i&gt;)</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wheat into flour, barley into pearl barley, soybeans into soybean oil, canola into canola oil, canola meal, or canola by-products, or sunflower seeds into sunflower oil; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the flour, pearl barley, oil, canola meal, or canola by-product manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing by that person; or selling manufactured seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing, to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state;
(c)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided otherwise in (c)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, beginning July 1, 2035, until January 1, 2046, dairy products; or selling dairy products that the person has manufactured to purchasers who either transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of state or purchasers who use such dairy products as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state or sold to a manufacturer for use as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The preferential tax rate provided to taxpayers under this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>does not apply to sales of dairy products on or after July 1, 2023, where a dairy product is used by the purchaser as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing in Washington of a dairy product;
(d)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, fruits or vegetables by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables, or selling at wholesale fruits or vegetables manufactured by the seller by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables and sold to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wood biomass fuel; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is equal to the value of wood biomass fuel manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. For the purposes of this section, &quot;wood biomass fuel&quot; means a liquid or gaseous fuel that is produced from lignocellulosic feedstocks, including wood, forest, or field residue and dedicated energy crops, and that does not include wood treated with chemical preservations such as creosote, pentachlorophenol, or copper-chrome-arsenic.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of splitting or processing dried peas; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the peas split or processed, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every nonprofit corporation and nonprofit association engaging within this state in research and development, as to such corporations and associations, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.484 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of slaughtering, breaking and/or processing perishable meat products and/or selling the same at wholesale only and not at retail; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was $250,000 or less; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was more than $250,000; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent through June 30, 2019, and 0.9 percent beginning July 1, 2019.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as an international steamship agent, international customs house broker, international freight forwarder, vessel and/or cargo charter broker in foreign commerce, and/or international air cargo agent; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to only international activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the movement of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent. Persons subject to taxation under this subsection are exempt from payment of taxes imposed by chapter
82.16
RCW for that portion of their business subject to taxation under this subsection. Stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the conduct of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce are defined as all activities of a labor, service or transportation nature whereby cargo may be loaded or unloaded to or from vessels or barges, passing over, onto or under a wharf, pier, or similar structure; cargo may be moved to a warehouse or similar holding or storage yard or area to await further movement in import or export or may move to a consolidation freight station and be stuffed, unstuffed, containerized, separated or otherwise segregated or aggregated for delivery or loaded on any mode of transportation for delivery to its consignee. Specific activities included in this definition are: Wharfage, handling, loading, unloading, moving of cargo to a convenient place of delivery to the consignee or a convenient place for further movement to export mode; documentation services in connection with the receipt, delivery, checking, care, custody and control of cargo required in the transfer of cargo; imported automobile handling prior to delivery to consignee; terminal stevedoring and incidental vessel services, including but not limited to plugging and unplugging refrigerator service to containers, trailers, and other refrigerated cargo receptacles, and securing ship hatch covers.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of disposing of low-level waste, as defined in RCW
70A.380.010
; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross income of the business, excluding any fees imposed under chapter
70A.384
RCW, multiplied by the rate of 3.3 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the gross income of the taxpayer is attributable to activities both within and without this state, the gross income attributable to this state must be determined in accordance with the methods of apportionment required under RCW
82.04.460
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state as an insurance producer or title insurance agent licensed under chapter
48.17
RCW or a surplus line broker licensed under chapter
48.15
RCW; as to such persons, the amount of the tax with respect to such licensed activities is equal to the gross income of such business multiplied by the rate of 0.484 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as a hospital, as defined in chapter
70.41
RCW, that is operated as a nonprofit corporation or by the state or any of its political subdivisions, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.75 percent through June 30, 1995, and 1.5 percent thereafter.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning October 1, 2005, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing commercial airplanes, or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.4235 percent from October 1, 2005, through June 30, 2007;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>0.2904 percent beginning July 1, 2007, through March 31, 2020; and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning April 1, 2020, 0.484 percent, subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies to all business activities described in this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2008, upon every person who is not eligible to report under the provisions of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and is engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of such tooling manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, be equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.2904 percent through March 31, 2020; and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning April 1, 2020, the following rates, which are subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>on the business of making retail sales of tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes; and
(B) 0.484 percent on all other business activities described in this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to all other requirements under this title, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
. However, this requirement does not apply to persons reporting under the tax rate in (a)(iii) of this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and 0.484 percent, respectively.
(ii) Nothing in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed as affecting the obligation of a person reporting under a tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
: (A) Pursuant to another provision of this title as a result of claiming a tax credit or exemption; or (B) pursuant to</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>as a result of claiming the tax rates in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for periods ending before April 1, 2020.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After March 31, 2021, the tax rates under (a)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must be reduced to 0.357 percent provided the conditions in RCW
82.04.2602
are met. The effective date of the rates authorized under this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>must occur on the first day of the next calendar quarter that is at least 60 days after the department receives the last of the two written notices pursuant to RCW
82.04.2602</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>are subject to the aerospace apprenticeship utilization rates required under RCW
49.04.220
by April 1, 2026, or five years after the effective date of the 0.357 percent rate authorized under this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of RCW
82.32.805
and
82.32.808
do not apply to this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in (f)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1, 2040.
(ii) With respect to the manufacturing of commercial airplanes or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes, this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1st of the year in which the department makes a determination that any final assembly or wing assembly of any version or variant of a commercial airplane that is the basis of a siting of a significant commercial airplane manufacturing program in the state under RCW
82.32.850
has been sited outside the state of Washington. This subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection, &quot;a significant commercial airplane manufacturer&quot; means a manufacturer of commercial airplanes with at least 50,000 full-time employees in Washington as of January 1, 2021.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of extracting timber or extracting for hire timber; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is, in the case of extractors, equal to the value of products, including by-products, extracted, or in the case of extractors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing or processing for hire:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber into timber products or wood products;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products into other timber products or wood products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling at wholesale:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber extracted by that person;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products manufactured by that person from timber or other timber products;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>wood products manufactured by that person from timber or timber products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>manufactured by that person; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross proceeds of sales of the timber, timber products, wood products, or products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling standing timber; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.2904 percent. For purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this subsection, the following definitions apply:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Biocomposite surface products&quot; means surface material products containing, by weight or volume, more than 50 percent recycled paper and that also use nonpetroleum-based phenolic resin as a bonding agent.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Paper and paper products&quot; means products made of interwoven cellulosic fibers held together largely by hydrogen bonding. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; includes newsprint; office, printing, fine, and pressure-sensitive papers; paper napkins, towels, and toilet tissue; kraft bag, construction, and other kraft industrial papers; paperboard, liquid packaging containers, containerboard, corrugated, and solid-fiber containers including linerboard and corrugated medium; and related types of cellulosic products containing primarily, by weight or volume, cellulosic materials. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; does not include books, newspapers, magazines, periodicals, and other printed publications, advertising materials, calendars, and similar types of printed materials.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Recycled paper&quot; means paper and paper products having 50 percent or more of their fiber content that comes from postconsumer waste. For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Timber&quot; means forest trees, standing or down, on privately or publicly owned land. &quot;Timber&quot; does not include Christmas trees that are cultivated by agricultural methods or short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Timber products&quot; means:
(A) Logs, wood chips, sawdust, wood waste, and similar products obtained wholly from the processing of timber, short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, or both;
(B) Pulp, including market pulp and pulp derived from recovered paper or paper products; and
(C) Recycled paper, but only when used in the manufacture of biocomposite surface products.
(vi) &quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v__subsec_vi">
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_f">
            <num>(f)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except for small harvesters as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed to affect the taxation of any activity defined as a retail sale in RCW
82.04.050</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or (c), defined as a wholesale sale in RCW
82.04.060</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in inspecting, testing, labeling, and storing canned salmon owned by another person, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.484 percent.
[
2023 c 422 s 5
;
2023 c 286 s 3
;
2022 c 16 s 140
;
2021 c 145 s 7
;
2020 c 165 s 3
. Prior:
2019 c 425 s 1
;
2019 c 336 s 4
;
2018 c 164 s 3
;
2017 c 135 s 11
; prior:
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 602
;
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 205
; prior:
2014 c 140 s 6
; (2014 c 140 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2014 c 140 s 4
; (2014 c 140 s 3 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6
; (2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203
; (2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202 expired July 1, 2015); prior: (2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 602 expired July 1, 2015);
2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 204
;
2011 c 2 s 203
(Initiative Measure No. 1107, approved November 2, 2010);
2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 506
; (2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 505 expired June 10, 2010);
2010 c 114 s 107
; prior:
2009 c 479 s 64
;
2009 c 461 s 1
;
2009 c 162 s 34
; prior:
2008 c 296 s 1
;
2008 c 217 s 100
;
2008 c 81 s 4
; prior:
2007 c 54 s 6
;
2007 c 48 s 2
; prior:
2006 c 354 s 4
;
2006 c 300 s 1
; prior:
2005 c 513 s 2
;
2005 c 443 s 4
; prior:
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 4
;
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 3
;
2003 c 339 s 11
;
2003 c 261 s 11
;
2001 2nd sp.s. c 25 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 312 s 5
;
1998 c 311 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 170 s 4
;
1996 c 148 s 2
;
1996 c 115 s 1
; prior:
1995 2nd sp.s. c 12 s 1
;
1995 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 1
;
1993 sp.s. c 25 s 104
;
1993 c 492 s 304
;
1991 c 272 s 15
;
1990 c 21 s 2
;
1987 c 139 s 1
; prior:
1985 c 471 s 1
;
1985 c 135 s 2
;
1983 2nd ex.s. c 3 s 5
; prior:
1983 1st ex.s. c 66 s 4
;
1983 1st ex.s. c 55 s 4
;
1982 2nd ex.s. c 13 s 1
;
1982 c 10 s 16
; prior:
1981 c 178 s 1
;
1981 c 172 s 3
;
1979 ex.s. c 196 s 2
;
1975 1st ex.s. c 291 s 7
;
1971 ex.s. c 281 s 5
;
1971 ex.s. c 186 s 3
;
1969 ex.s. c 262 s 36
;
1967 ex.s. c 1</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that over the last fifteen years, technological transformation and other developments have radically changed the newspaper industry business model, which remains in transition. The legislature further finds that the economic hardship wrought by this digital transformation has been substantial. The legislature finds that a strong and vibrant newspaper industry in Washington is beneficial to the state's citizens and to the conduct of good government at every level. The legislature further finds that advertising revenue of all United States newspapers fell from 63.5 billion dollars in 2000 to about twenty-three billion dollars in 2013, and is still falling. The legislature further finds that traditional news organizations' ability to support high quality news gathering and reporting relied primarily on a model in which advertisers paid to reach mass audiences attracted by newspapers. The legislature further finds that advertisers found it advantageous to pay to reach a mass audience because other advertising mediums were limited and less effective. The digital era has greatly fractured traditional spending by advertisers and turned this model on its head such that newspapers continue to require time to adapt so they may continue their public service mission. The legislature also finds that the business and occupation tax rate for the newspaper industry was pegged to the general manufacturing and wholesaling rate from 1937 until 2009, when the legislature extended tax relief to the industry due to this shift. It is the legislature's intent to extend this tax relief to the industry until its revenues and business model have stabilized. It is the legislature's further intent to provide a uniform tax rate for the industry to minimize the burden of reporting state business and occupation taxes for different types of revenue, which oftentimes are impossible to account for separately by the taxpayer.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This subsection is the tax preference performance statement for the newspaper tax preferences in section 602 of this act. The performance statement is only intended to be used for subsequent evaluation of the tax preference. It is not intended to create a private right of action by any party or be used to determine eligibility for preferential tax treatment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The legislature categorizes this tax preference as one intended to provide temporary tax relief as described in RCW
82.32.808</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It is the legislature's specific public policy objective to provide business and occupation tax relief to the newspaper industry as it continues to adjust to significant revenue shifts and technological changes. As a secondary public policy objective, it is the legislature's intent to provide a permanent uniform rate for the industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To measure the effectiveness of the preference provided in this act in achieving the specific public policy objective described in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee must evaluate year-to-year changes in gross revenue derived from all sources for newspaper firms claiming the preferential tax rate under RCW
82.04.260</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The information provided in the annual tax preference accountability report submitted by taxpayers as required by the department of revenue and taxpayer data provided by the department of revenue is intended to provide the informational basis for the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the data source described under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee may use any other data it deems necessary in performing the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 601
.]
Effective dates
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 ss 202-205:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Contingent effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 6:
&quot;Section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 39
.]
Contingent expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 5:
&quot;Section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 38
.]
Effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 4:
&quot;Section 4 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 37
.]
Expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 3:
&quot;Section 3 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 36
.]
Effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 16
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 15
.]
Contingent effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See RCW
82.32.850
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See note following RCW
82.32.850
.
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203:
&quot;Section 203 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1902
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202:
&quot;Section 202 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1901
.]
Intent
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13:
&quot;The intent of part II of this act is to incentivize the creation of additional jobs in Washington in the dairy industry and related industries that manufacture dairy-based products. More specifically, it is the intent of part II of this act to encourage infant formula producers to locate new facilities in Washington or expand existing facilities in Washington through an extension of a preferential business and occupation tax </p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wheat into flour, barley into pearl barley, soybeans into soybean oil, canola into canola oil, canola meal, or canola by-products, or sunflower seeds into sunflower oil; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the flour, pearl barley, oil, canola meal, or canola by-product manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing by that person; or selling manufactured seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing, to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state;
(c)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided otherwise in (c)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, beginning July 1, 2035, until January 1, 2046, dairy products; or selling dairy products that the person has manufactured to purchasers who either transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of state or purchasers who use such dairy products as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state or sold to a manufacturer for use as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The preferential tax rate provided to taxpayers under this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>does not apply to sales of dairy products on or after July 1, 2023, where a dairy product is used by the purchaser as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing in Washington of a dairy product;
(d)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, fruits or vegetables by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables, or selling at wholesale fruits or vegetables manufactured by the seller by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables and sold to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wood biomass fuel; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is equal to the value of wood biomass fuel manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. For the purposes of this section, &quot;wood biomass fuel&quot; means a liquid or gaseous fuel that is produced from lignocellulosic feedstocks, including wood, forest, or field residue and dedicated energy crops, and that does not include wood treated with chemical preservations such as creosote, pentachlorophenol, or copper-chrome-arsenic.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of splitting or processing dried peas; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the peas split or processed, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every nonprofit corporation and nonprofit association engaging within this state in research and development, as to such corporations and associations, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.484 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of slaughtering, breaking and/or processing perishable meat products and/or selling the same at wholesale only and not at retail; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was $250,000 or less; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was more than $250,000; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent through June 30, 2019, and 0.9 percent beginning July 1, 2019.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as an international steamship agent, international customs house broker, international freight forwarder, vessel and/or cargo charter broker in foreign commerce, and/or international air cargo agent; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to only international activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the movement of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent. Persons subject to taxation under this subsection are exempt from payment of taxes imposed by chapter
82.16
RCW for that portion of their business subject to taxation under this subsection. Stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the conduct of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce are defined as all activities of a labor, service or transportation nature whereby cargo may be loaded or unloaded to or from vessels or barges, passing over, onto or under a wharf, pier, or similar structure; cargo may be moved to a warehouse or similar holding or storage yard or area to await further movement in import or export or may move to a consolidation freight station and be stuffed, unstuffed, containerized, separated or otherwise segregated or aggregated for delivery or loaded on any mode of transportation for delivery to its consignee. Specific activities included in this definition are: Wharfage, handling, loading, unloading, moving of cargo to a convenient place of delivery to the consignee or a convenient place for further movement to export mode; documentation services in connection with the receipt, delivery, checking, care, custody and control of cargo required in the transfer of cargo; imported automobile handling prior to delivery to consignee; terminal stevedoring and incidental vessel services, including but not limited to plugging and unplugging refrigerator service to containers, trailers, and other refrigerated cargo receptacles, and securing ship hatch covers.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of disposing of low-level waste, as defined in RCW
70A.380.010
; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross income of the business, excluding any fees imposed under chapter
70A.384
RCW, multiplied by the rate of 3.3 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the gross income of the taxpayer is attributable to activities both within and without this state, the gross income attributable to this state must be determined in accordance with the methods of apportionment required under RCW
82.04.460
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state as an insurance producer licensed under chapter
48.17
RCW or a surplus line broker licensed under chapter
48.15
RCW; as to such persons, the amount of the tax with respect to such licensed activities is equal to the gross income of such business multiplied by the rate of 0.484 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as a hospital, as defined in chapter
70.41
RCW, that is operated as a nonprofit corporation or by the state or any of its political subdivisions, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.75 percent through June 30, 1995, and 1.5 percent thereafter.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning October 1, 2005, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing commercial airplanes, or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.4235 percent from October 1, 2005, through June 30, 2007;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>0.2904 percent beginning July 1, 2007, through March 31, 2020; and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning April 1, 2020, 0.484 percent, subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies to all business activities described in this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2008, upon every person who is not eligible to report under the provisions of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and is engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of such tooling manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, be equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.2904 percent through March 31, 2020; and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning April 1, 2020, the following rates, which are subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>on the business of making retail sales of tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes; and
(B) 0.484 percent on all other business activities described in this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to all other requirements under this title, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
. However, this requirement does not apply to persons reporting under the tax rate in (a)(iii) of this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and 0.484 percent, respectively.
(ii) Nothing in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed as affecting the obligation of a person reporting under a tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
: (A) Pursuant to another provision of this title as a result of claiming a tax credit or exemption; or (B) pursuant to</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>as a result of claiming the tax rates in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for periods ending before April 1, 2020.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After March 31, 2021, the tax rates under (a)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must be reduced to 0.357 percent provided the conditions in RCW
82.04.2602
are met. The effective date of the rates authorized under this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>must occur on the first day of the next calendar quarter that is at least 60 days after the department receives the last of the two written notices pursuant to RCW
82.04.2602</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>are subject to the aerospace apprenticeship utilization rates required under RCW
49.04.220
by April 1, 2026, or five years after the effective date of the 0.357 percent rate authorized under this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of RCW
82.32.805
and
82.32.808
do not apply to this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in (f)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1, 2040.
(ii) With respect to the manufacturing of commercial airplanes or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes, this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1st of the year in which the department makes a determination that any final assembly or wing assembly of any version or variant of a commercial airplane that is the basis of a siting of a significant commercial airplane manufacturing program in the state under RCW
82.32.850
has been sited outside the state of Washington. This subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection, &quot;a significant commercial airplane manufacturer&quot; means a manufacturer of commercial airplanes with at least 50,000 full-time employees in Washington as of January 1, 2021.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of extracting timber or extracting for hire timber; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is, in the case of extractors, equal to the value of products, including by-products, extracted, or in the case of extractors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing or processing for hire:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber into timber products or wood products;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products into other timber products or wood products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling at wholesale:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber extracted by that person;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products manufactured by that person from timber or other timber products;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>wood products manufactured by that person from timber or timber products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>manufactured by that person; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross proceeds of sales of the timber, timber products, wood products, or products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling standing timber; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.2904 percent. For purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this subsection, the following definitions apply:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Biocomposite surface products&quot; means surface material products containing, by weight or volume, more than 50 percent recycled paper and that also use nonpetroleum-based phenolic resin as a bonding agent.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Paper and paper products&quot; means products made of interwoven cellulosic fibers held together largely by hydrogen bonding. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; includes newsprint; office, printing, fine, and pressure-sensitive papers; paper napkins, towels, and toilet tissue; kraft bag, construction, and other kraft industrial papers; paperboard, liquid packaging containers, containerboard, corrugated, and solid-fiber containers including linerboard and corrugated medium; and related types of cellulosic products containing primarily, by weight or volume, cellulosic materials. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; does not include books, newspapers, magazines, periodicals, and other printed publications, advertising materials, calendars, and similar types of printed materials.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Recycled paper&quot; means paper and paper products having 50 percent or more of their fiber content that comes from postconsumer waste. For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Timber&quot; means forest trees, standing or down, on privately or publicly owned land. &quot;Timber&quot; does not include Christmas trees that are cultivated by agricultural methods or short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Timber products&quot; means:
(A) Logs, wood chips, sawdust, wood waste, and similar products obtained wholly from the processing of timber, short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, or both;
(B) Pulp, including market pulp and pulp derived from recovered paper or paper products; and
(C) Recycled paper, but only when used in the manufacture of biocomposite surface products.
(vi) &quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v__subsec_vi">
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_f">
            <num>(f)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except for small harvesters as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed to affect the taxation of any activity defined as a retail sale in RCW
82.04.050</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or (c), defined as a wholesale sale in RCW
82.04.060</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in inspecting, testing, labeling, and storing canned salmon owned by another person, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.484 percent.
[
2025 c 423 s 101
. Prior:
2023 c 422 s 5
;
2023 c 286 s 3
;
2022 c 16 s 140
;
2021 c 145 s 7
;
2020 c 165 s 3
; prior:
2019 c 425 s 1
;
2019 c 336 s 4
;
2018 c 164 s 3
;
2017 c 135 s 11
; prior:
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 602
;
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 205
; prior:
2014 c 140 s 6
; (2014 c 140 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2014 c 140 s 4
; (2014 c 140 s 3 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6
; (2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203
; (2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202 expired July 1, 2015); prior: (2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 602 expired July 1, 2015);
2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 204
;
2011 c 2 s 203
(Initiative Measure No. 1107, approved November 2, 2010);
2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 506
; (2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 505 expired June 10, 2010);
2010 c 114 s 107
; prior:
2009 c 479 s 64
;
2009 c 461 s 1
;
2009 c 162 s 34
; prior:
2008 c 296 s 1
;
2008 c 217 s 100
;
2008 c 81 s 4
; prior:
2007 c 54 s 6
;
2007 c 48 s 2
; prior:
2006 c 354 s 4
;
2006 c 300 s 1
; prior:
2005 c 513 s 2
;
2005 c 443 s 4
; prior:
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 4
;
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 3
;
2003 c 339 s 11
;
2003 c 261 s 11
;
2001 2nd sp.s. c 25 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 312 s 5
;
1998 c 311 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 170 s 4
;
1996 c 148 s 2
;
1996 c 115 s 1
; prior:
1995 2nd sp.s. c 12 s 1
;
1995 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 1
;
1993 sp.s. c 25 s 104
;
1993 c 492 s 304
;
1991 c 272 s 15
;
1990 c 21 s 2
;
1987 c 139 s 1
; prior:
1985 c 471 s 1
;
1985 c 135 s 2
;
1983 2nd ex.s. c 3 s 5
; prior:
1983 1st ex.s. c 66 s 4
;
1983 1st ex.s. c 55 s 4
;
1982 2nd ex.s. c 13 s 1
;
1982 c 10 s 16
; prior:
1981 c 178 s 1
;
1981 c 172 s 3
;
1979 ex.s. c 196 s 2
;
1975 1st ex.s. c 291 s 7
;
1971 ex.s. c 281 s 5
;
1971 ex.s. c 186 s 3
;
1969 ex.s. c</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_13__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that, according to the most recent tax exemption study published by the department of revenue, there are currently 786 tax exemptions for the major state and local tax sources in Washington. The exemptions result in nearly $200,000,000,000 of taxpayer savings for the current biennium. The legislature acknowledges that certain tax preferences, such as the sales and use tax exemption for food and the working families tax credit, are intended to rebalance Washington's tax code for working people. However, the legislature further acknowledges that many existing tax preferences are the result of private interests securing preferential tax treatment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For that reason, the legislature enacted robust tax preference performance measures to create greater tax preference transparency and accountability and provide a framework for legislators to make informed decisions on the most efficient use of taxpayer dollars. To ensure tax exemptions meet certain public policy objectives, the joint legislative audit and review committee, a nonpartisan legislative agency, routinely evaluates tax preferences based on specific criteria provided in law and reports that information to the legislature each year. The reports provide accurate, comprehensive, unbiased data that policymakers may use to determine if a tax preference should be continued, modified, or repealed. Additionally, the citizen commission for performance measurement of tax preferences is responsible for selecting which tax preferences are reviewed each year and provides comment on the legislative auditor's reports. Both entities provide recommendations to the legislature on the effectiveness of a tax preference in meeting certain performance measures.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Furthermore, the department of revenue assists in the tax preference evaluation process by collecting data from taxpayer beneficiaries and regularly reviewing changes in state and federal law. The analysis by the department and legislative auditor often reveals that a tax exemption is legally obsolete, meaning the specific legal conditions that existed when the exemption was enacted have since changed and the original legislative intent is no longer applicable. Additionally, some tax exemptions are simply not used and should be removed from the tax code to create better clarity for taxpayers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature recognizes that more progress is needed for the state to have a fair and balanced tax system that provides sustainable and ample funding for public schools, health care, and other programs that protect the safety and well-being of the public, as well as social services that provide critical, basic-needs assistance for our state's most vulnerable residents. The legislature further recognizes that the tax preference performance review process provides an opportunity for policymakers to evaluate the tax code to ensure the state is not losing essential revenue due to inefficient or no longer applicable tax exemptions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Thus, the legislature intends to enact recommendations from the joint legislative audit and review committee, the citizen commission for performance measurement of tax preferences, and the department of revenue, including eliminating several obsolete tax preferences, clarifying legislative intent to better inform future tax preference performance reviews, adding expiration dates, and other actions aimed at creating a fair and balanced tax system.&quot; [
2025 c 423 s 1
.]
Necessity of act
—
2025 c 423:
&quot;This act is necessary for the support of the state government and its existing public institutions.&quot; [
2025 c 423 s 402
.]
Tax preference performance statement
—
2023 c 422 ss 2-5:
See note following RCW
82.04.4268
.
Findings
—
Effective date
—
Expiration date
—
2023 c 286:
See notes following RCW
82.04.759
.
Intent
—
Finding
—
2022 c 16:
See note following RCW
69.50.101
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
Effective date
—
2020 c 165:
See notes following RCW
82.04.2602
.
Effective date
—
2019 c 425:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 2019.&quot; [
2019 c 425 s 2
.]
Findings
—
Intent
—
2019 c 336:
See notes following RCW
82.04.261
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
Effective date
—
2018 c 164:
See notes following RCW
82.08.900
.
Effective date
—
2017 c 135:
See note following RCW
82.32.534
.
Expiration date
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6; 2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 602:
&quot;Section 602 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 603
;
2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 704
.]
Findings
—
Intent
—
Tax preference performance statement
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 602:
&quot;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that over the last fifteen years, technological transformation and other developments have radically changed the newspaper industry business model, which remains in transition. The legislature further finds that the economic hardship wrought by this digital transformation has been substantial. The legislature finds that a strong and vibrant newspaper industry in Washington is beneficial to the state's citizens and to the conduct of good government at every level. The legislature further finds that advertising revenue of all United States newspapers fell from 63.5 billion dollars in 2000 to about twenty-three billion dollars in 2013, and is still falling. The legislature further finds that traditional news organizations' ability to support high quality news gathering and reporting relied primarily on a model in which advertisers paid to reach mass audiences attracted by newspapers. The legislature further finds that advertisers found it advantageous to pay to reach a mass audience because other advertising mediums were limited and less effective. The digital era has greatly fractured traditional spending by advertisers and turned this model on its head such that newspapers continue to require time to adapt so they may continue their public service mission. The legislature also finds that the business and occupation tax rate for the newspaper industry was pegged to the general manufacturing and wholesaling rate from 1937 until 2009, when the legislature extended tax relief to the industry due to this shift. It is the legislature's intent to extend this tax relief to the industry until its revenues and business model have stabilized. It is the legislature's further intent to provide a uniform tax rate for the industry to minimize the burden of reporting state business and occupation taxes for different types of revenue, which oftentimes are impossible to account for separately by the taxpayer.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This subsection is the tax preference performance statement for the newspaper tax preferences in section 602 of this act. The performance statement is only intended to be used for subsequent evaluation of the tax preference. It is not intended to create a private right of action by any party or be used to determine eligibility for preferential tax treatment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The legislature categorizes this tax preference as one intended to provide temporary tax relief as described in RCW
82.32.808</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It is the legislature's specific public policy objective to provide business and occupation tax relief to the newspaper industry as it continues to adjust to significant revenue shifts and technological changes. As a secondary public policy objective, it is the legislature's intent to provide a permanent uniform rate for the industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To measure the effectiveness of the preference provided in this act in achieving the specific public policy objective described in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee must evaluate year-to-year changes in gross revenue derived from all sources for newspaper firms claiming the preferential tax rate under RCW
82.04.260</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The information provided in the annual tax preference accountability report submitted by taxpayers as required by the department of revenue and taxpayer data provided by the department of revenue is intended to provide the informational basis for the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the data source described under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee may use any other data it deems necessary in performing the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 601
.]
Effective dates
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 ss 202-205:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Contingent effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 6:
&quot;Section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 39
.]
Contingent expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 5:
&quot;Section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 38
.]
Effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 4:
&quot;Section 4 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 37
.]
Expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 3:
&quot;Section 3 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 36
.]
Effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 16
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 15
.]
Contingent effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See RCW
82.32.850
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See note following RCW
82.32.850
.
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203:
&quot;Section 203 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1902
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202:
&quot;Section 202 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1901
.]
Intent
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13:
&quot;The intent of part II of this act is to incentivize the creation of additional jobs in Washington in the dairy industry and related industries that manufacture dairy-based products. More specifically, it is the intent of part II of this act to encourage infant formula producers to locate new facilities in Washington or expand existing facilities in Washington through an extension of a preferential business and occupation tax </p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wheat into flour, barley into pearl barley, soybeans into soybean oil, canola into canola oil, canola meal, or canola by-products, or sunflower seeds into sunflower oil; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the flour, pearl barley, oil, canola meal, or canola by-product manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing by that person; or selling manufactured seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing, to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state;
(c)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided otherwise in (c)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, beginning July 1, 2035, until January 1, 2046, dairy products; or selling dairy products that the person has manufactured to purchasers who either transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of state or purchasers who use such dairy products as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state or sold to a manufacturer for use as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The preferential tax rate provided to taxpayers under this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>does not apply to sales of dairy products on or after July 1, 2023, where a dairy product is used by the purchaser as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing in Washington of a dairy product;
(d)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, fruits or vegetables by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables, or selling at wholesale fruits or vegetables manufactured by the seller by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables and sold to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wood biomass fuel; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is equal to the value of wood biomass fuel manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. For the purposes of this section, &quot;wood biomass fuel&quot; means a liquid or gaseous fuel that is produced from lignocellulosic feedstocks, including wood, forest, or field residue and dedicated energy crops, and that does not include wood treated with chemical preservations such as creosote, pentachlorophenol, or copper-chrome-arsenic.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of splitting or processing dried peas; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the peas split or processed, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every nonprofit corporation and nonprofit association engaging within this state in research and development, as to such corporations and associations, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.5 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of slaughtering, breaking and/or processing perishable meat products and/or selling the same at wholesale only and not at retail; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was $250,000 or less; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was more than $250,000; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent through June 30, 2019, and 0.9 percent beginning July 1, 2019.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as an international steamship agent, international customs house broker, international freight forwarder, vessel and/or cargo charter broker in foreign commerce, and/or international air cargo agent; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to only international activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the movement of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent. Persons subject to taxation under this subsection are exempt from payment of taxes imposed by chapter
82.16
RCW for that portion of their business subject to taxation under this subsection. Stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the conduct of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce are defined as all activities of a labor, service or transportation nature whereby cargo may be loaded or unloaded to or from vessels or barges, passing over, onto or under a wharf, pier, or similar structure; cargo may be moved to a warehouse or similar holding or storage yard or area to await further movement in import or export or may move to a consolidation freight station and be stuffed, unstuffed, containerized, separated or otherwise segregated or aggregated for delivery or loaded on any mode of transportation for delivery to its consignee. Specific activities included in this definition are: Wharfage, handling, loading, unloading, moving of cargo to a convenient place of delivery to the consignee or a convenient place for further movement to export mode; documentation services in connection with the receipt, delivery, checking, care, custody and control of cargo required in the transfer of cargo; imported automobile handling prior to delivery to consignee; terminal stevedoring and incidental vessel services, including but not limited to plugging and unplugging refrigerator service to containers, trailers, and other refrigerated cargo receptacles, and securing ship hatch covers.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of disposing of low-level waste, as defined in RCW
70A.380.010
; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross income of the business, excluding any fees imposed under chapter
70A.384
RCW, multiplied by the rate of 3.3 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the gross income of the taxpayer is attributable to activities both within and without this state, the gross income attributable to this state must be determined in accordance with the methods of apportionment required under RCW
82.04.460
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state as an insurance producer licensed under chapter
48.17
RCW or a surplus line broker licensed under chapter
48.15
RCW; as to such persons, the amount of the tax with respect to such licensed activities is equal to the gross income of such business multiplied by the rate of 0.5 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as a hospital, as defined in chapter
70.41
RCW, that is operated as a nonprofit corporation or by the state or any of its political subdivisions, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.75 percent through June 30, 1995, and 1.5 percent thereafter.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning October 1, 2005, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing commercial airplanes, or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.4235 percent from October 1, 2005, through June 30, 2007;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>0.2904 percent beginning July 1, 2007, through March 31, 2020; and
(iii)(A) Beginning April 1, 2020, through December 31, 2026, 0.484 percent, subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies to all business activities described in this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies to all business activities described in this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2008, upon every person who is not eligible to report under the provisions of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and is engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of such tooling manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, be equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.2904 percent through March 31, 2020;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning April 1, 2020, through December 31, 2026, the following rates, which are subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>on the business of making retail sales of tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes; and
(B) 0.484 percent on all other business activities described in this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>on the business of making retail sales of tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes; and
(B) 0.5 percent on all other business activities described in this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to all other requirements under this title, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
. However, this requirement does not apply to persons reporting under the tax rate in (a)(iii) of this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and 0.5 percent, respectively.
(ii) Nothing in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed as affecting the obligation of a person reporting under a tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
: (A) Pursuant to another provision of this title as a result of claiming a tax credit or exemption; or (B) pursuant to</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>as a result of claiming the tax rates in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for periods ending before April 1, 2020.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After March 31, 2021, the tax rates under (a)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must be reduced to 0.357 percent provided the conditions in RCW
82.04.2602
are met. The effective date of the rates authorized under this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>must occur on the first day of the next calendar quarter that is at least 60 days after the department receives the last of the two written notices pursuant to RCW
82.04.2602</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>are subject to the aerospace apprenticeship utilization rates required under RCW
49.04.220
by April 1, 2026, or five years after the effective date of the 0.357 percent rate authorized under this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of RCW
82.32.805
and
82.32.808
do not apply to this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in (f)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1, 2040.
(ii) With respect to the manufacturing of commercial airplanes or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes, this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1st of the year in which the department makes a determination that any final assembly or wing assembly of any version or variant of a commercial airplane that is the basis of a siting of a significant commercial airplane manufacturing program in the state under RCW
82.32.850
has been sited outside the state of Washington. This subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection, &quot;a significant commercial airplane manufacturer&quot; means a manufacturer of commercial airplanes with at least 50,000 full-time employees in Washington as of January 1, 2021.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of extracting timber or extracting for hire timber; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is, in the case of extractors, equal to the value of products, including by-products, extracted, or in the case of extractors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing or processing for hire:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber into timber products or wood products;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products into other timber products or wood products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling at wholesale:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber extracted by that person;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products manufactured by that person from timber or other timber products;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>wood products manufactured by that person from timber or timber products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>manufactured by that person; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross proceeds of sales of the timber, timber products, wood products, or products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling standing timber; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.2904 percent. For purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this subsection, the following definitions apply:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Biocomposite surface products&quot; means surface material products containing, by weight or volume, more than 50 percent recycled paper and that also use nonpetroleum-based phenolic resin as a bonding agent.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Paper and paper products&quot; means products made of interwoven cellulosic fibers held together largely by hydrogen bonding. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; includes newsprint; office, printing, fine, and pressure-sensitive papers; paper napkins, towels, and toilet tissue; kraft bag, construction, and other kraft industrial papers; paperboard, liquid packaging containers, containerboard, corrugated, and solid-fiber containers including linerboard and corrugated medium; and related types of cellulosic products containing primarily, by weight or volume, cellulosic materials. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; does not include books, newspapers, magazines, periodicals, and other printed publications, advertising materials, calendars, and similar types of printed materials.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Recycled paper&quot; means paper and paper products having 50 percent or more of their fiber content that comes from postconsumer waste. For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Timber&quot; means forest trees, standing or down, on privately or publicly owned land. &quot;Timber&quot; does not include Christmas trees that are cultivated by agricultural methods or short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Timber products&quot; means:
(A) Logs, wood chips, sawdust, wood waste, and similar products obtained wholly from the processing of timber, short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, or both;
(B) Pulp, including market pulp and pulp derived from recovered paper or paper products; and
(C) Recycled paper, but only when used in the manufacture of biocomposite surface products.
(vi) &quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v__subsec_vi">
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_f">
            <num>(f)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except for small harvesters as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed to affect the taxation of any activity defined as a retail sale in RCW
82.04.050</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or (c), defined as a wholesale sale in RCW
82.04.060</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in inspecting, testing, labeling, and storing canned salmon owned by another person, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.5 percent.
[
2025 c 423 s 101
;
2025 c 420 s 112
. Prior:
2023 c 422 s 5
;
2023 c 286 s 3
;
2022 c 16 s 140
;
2021 c 145 s 7
;
2020 c 165 s 3
; prior:
2019 c 425 s 1
;
2019 c 336 s 4
;
2018 c 164 s 3
;
2017 c 135 s 11
; prior:
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 602
;
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 205
; prior:
2014 c 140 s 6
; (2014 c 140 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2014 c 140 s 4
; (2014 c 140 s 3 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6
; (2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203
; (2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202 expired July 1, 2015); prior: (2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 602 expired July 1, 2015);
2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 204
;
2011 c 2 s 203
(Initiative Measure No. 1107, approved November 2, 2010);
2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 506
; (2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 505 expired June 10, 2010);
2010 c 114 s 107
; prior:
2009 c 479 s 64
;
2009 c 461 s 1
;
2009 c 162 s 34
; prior:
2008 c 296 s 1
;
2008 c 217 s 100
;
2008 c 81 s 4
; prior:
2007 c 54 s 6
;
2007 c 48 s 2
; prior:
2006 c 354 s 4
;
2006 c 300 s 1
; prior:
2005 c 513 s 2
;
2005 c 443 s 4
; prior:
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 4
;
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 3
;
2003 c 339 s 11
;
2003 c 261 s 11
;
2001 2nd sp.s. c 25 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 312 s 5
;
1998 c 311 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 170 s 4
;
1996 c 148 s 2
;
1996 c 115 s 1
; prior:
1995 2nd sp.s. c 12 s 1
;
1995 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 1
;
1993 sp.s. c 25 s 104
;
1993 c 492 s 304
;
1991 c 272 s 15
;
1990 c 21 s 2
;
1987 c 139 s 1
; prior:
1985 c 471 s 1
;
1985 c 135 s 2
;
1983 2nd ex.s. c 3 s 5
; prior:
1983 1st ex.s. c 66 s 4
;
1983 1st ex.s. c 55 s 4
;
1982 2nd ex.s. c 13 s 1
;
1982 c 10 s 16
; prior:
1981 c 178 s 1
;
1981 c 172 s 3
;
1979 ex.s. c 196 s 2
;
1975 1st ex.s. c 291 s 7
;
1971 ex.s. c 281 s 5
;
1971 ex.s. c 186 s</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>RCW
82.04.280
was amended by 2025 c 9 s 2, changing subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section was amended by 2025 c 420 s 112 and by 2025 c 423 s 101, each without reference to the other. Both amendments are incorporated in the publication of this section under RCW
1.12.025</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that, according to the most recent tax exemption study published by the department of revenue, there are currently 786 tax exemptions for the major state and local tax sources in Washington. The exemptions result in nearly $200,000,000,000 of taxpayer savings for the current biennium. The legislature acknowledges that certain tax preferences, such as the sales and use tax exemption for food and the working families tax credit, are intended to rebalance Washington's tax code for working people. However, the legislature further acknowledges that many existing tax preferences are the result of private interests securing preferential tax treatment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For that reason, the legislature enacted robust tax preference performance measures to create greater tax preference transparency and accountability and provide a framework for legislators to make informed decisions on the most efficient use of taxpayer dollars. To ensure tax exemptions meet certain public policy objectives, the joint legislative audit and review committee, a nonpartisan legislative agency, routinely evaluates tax preferences based on specific criteria provided in law and reports that information to the legislature each year. The reports provide accurate, comprehensive, unbiased data that policymakers may use to determine if a tax preference should be continued, modified, or repealed. Additionally, the citizen commission for performance measurement of tax preferences is responsible for selecting which tax preferences are reviewed each year and provides comment on the legislative auditor's reports. Both entities provide recommendations to the legislature on the effectiveness of a tax preference in meeting certain performance measures.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Furthermore, the department of revenue assists in the tax preference evaluation process by collecting data from taxpayer beneficiaries and regularly reviewing changes in state and federal law. The analysis by the department and legislative auditor often reveals that a tax exemption is legally obsolete, meaning the specific legal conditions that existed when the exemption was enacted have since changed and the original legislative intent is no longer applicable. Additionally, some tax exemptions are simply not used and should be removed from the tax code to create better clarity for taxpayers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature recognizes that more progress is needed for the state to have a fair and balanced tax system that provides sustainable and ample funding for public schools, health care, and other programs that protect the safety and well-being of the public, as well as social services that provide critical, basic-needs assistance for our state's most vulnerable residents. The legislature further recognizes that the tax preference performance review process provides an opportunity for policymakers to evaluate the tax code to ensure the state is not losing essential revenue due to inefficient or no longer applicable tax exemptions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Thus, the legislature intends to enact recommendations from the joint legislative audit and review committee, the citizen commission for performance measurement of tax preferences, and the department of revenue, including eliminating several obsolete tax preferences, clarifying legislative intent to better inform future tax preference performance reviews, adding expiration dates, and other actions aimed at creating a fair and balanced tax system.&quot; [
2025 c 423 s 1
.]
Necessity of act
—
2025 c 423:
&quot;This act is necessary for the support of the state government and its existing public institutions.&quot; [
2025 c 423 s 402
.]
Expiration date
—
2025 c 420 s 112:
&quot;Section 112 of this act expires January 1, 2034.&quot; [
2025 c 420 s 506
.]
Effective date
—
2025 c 420 ss 101-108 and 110-112:
See note following RCW
82.04.230
.
Tax preference performance statement exemption
—
Automatic expiration date exemption
—
Necessity of act
—
2025 c 420:
See notes following RCW
82.04.230
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
2023 c 422 ss 2-5:
See note following RCW
82.04.4268
.
Findings
—
Effective date
—
Expiration date
—
2023 c 286:
See notes following RCW
82.04.759
.
Intent
—
Finding
—
2022 c 16:
See note following RCW
69.50.101
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
Effective date
—
2020 c 165:
See notes following RCW
82.04.2602
.
Effective date
—
2019 c 425:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 2019.&quot; [
2019 c 425 s 2
.]
Findings
—
Intent
—
2019 c 336:
See notes following RCW
82.04.261
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
Effective date
—
2018 c 164:
See notes following RCW
82.08.900
.
Effective date
—
2017 c 135:
See note following RCW
82.32.534
.
Expiration date
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6; 2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 602:
&quot;Section 602 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 603
;
2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 704
.]
Findings
—
Intent
—
Tax prefere</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that over the last fifteen years, technological transformation and other developments have radically changed the newspaper industry business model, which remains in transition. The legislature further finds that the economic hardship wrought by this digital transformation has been substantial. The legislature finds that a strong and vibrant newspaper industry in Washington is beneficial to the state's citizens and to the conduct of good government at every level. The legislature further finds that advertising revenue of all United States newspapers fell from 63.5 billion dollars in 2000 to about twenty-three billion dollars in 2013, and is still falling. The legislature further finds that traditional news organizations' ability to support high quality news gathering and reporting relied primarily on a model in which advertisers paid to reach mass audiences attracted by newspapers. The legislature further finds that advertisers found it advantageous to pay to reach a mass audience because other advertising mediums were limited and less effective. The digital era has greatly fractured traditional spending by advertisers and turned this model on its head such that newspapers continue to require time to adapt so they may continue their public service mission. The legislature also finds that the business and occupation tax rate for the newspaper industry was pegged to the general manufacturing and wholesaling rate from 1937 until 2009, when the legislature extended tax relief to the industry due to this shift. It is the legislature's intent to extend this tax relief to the industry until its revenues and business model have stabilized. It is the legislature's further intent to provide a uniform tax rate for the industry to minimize the burden of reporting state business and occupation taxes for different types of revenue, which oftentimes are impossible to account for separately by the taxpayer.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This subsection is the tax preference performance statement for the newspaper tax preferences in section 602 of this act. The performance statement is only intended to be used for subsequent evaluation of the tax preference. It is not intended to create a private right of action by any party or be used to determine eligibility for preferential tax treatment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The legislature categorizes this tax preference as one intended to provide temporary tax relief as described in RCW
82.32.808</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It is the legislature's specific public policy objective to provide business and occupation tax relief to the newspaper industry as it continues to adjust to significant revenue shifts and technological changes. As a secondary public policy objective, it is the legislature's intent to provide a permanent uniform rate for the industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To measure the effectiveness of the preference provided in this act in achieving the specific public policy objective described in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee must evaluate year-to-year changes in gross revenue derived from all sources for newspaper firms claiming the preferential tax rate under RCW
82.04.260</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The information provided in the annual tax preference accountability report submitted by taxpayers as required by the department of revenue and taxpayer data provided by the department of revenue is intended to provide the informational basis for the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the data source described under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee may use any other data it deems necessary in performing the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 601
.]
Effective dates
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 ss 202-205:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Contingent effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 6:
&quot;Section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 39
.]
Contingent expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 5:
&quot;Section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 38
.]
Effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 4:
&quot;Section 4 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 37
.]
Expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 3:
&quot;Section 3 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 36
.]
Effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 16
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 15
.]
Contingent effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See RCW
82.32.850
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See note following RCW
82.32.850
.
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203:
&quot;Section 203 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1902
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202:
&quot;Section 202 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1901
.]
Intent
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13:
&quot;The intent of part II of this act is to incentivize the creation of additional jobs in Washington in the dairy industry and related industries that manufacture dairy-based products. More specifically, it is the intent of part II of this act to encourage infant formula producers to locate new facilities in Washington or expand existing facilities in Washington through an extension of a preferential business and occupation tax </p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wheat into flour, barley into pearl barley, soybeans into soybean oil, canola into canola oil, canola meal, or canola by-products, or sunflower seeds into sunflower oil; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the flour, pearl barley, oil, canola meal, or canola by-product manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing by that person; or selling manufactured seafood products that remain in a raw, raw frozen, or raw salted state at the completion of the manufacturing, to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state;
(c)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided otherwise in (c)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, beginning July 1, 2035, until January 1, 2046, dairy products; or selling dairy products that the person has manufactured to purchasers who either transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of state or purchasers who use such dairy products as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state or sold to a manufacturer for use as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing of a dairy product.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The preferential tax rate provided to taxpayers under this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>does not apply to sales of dairy products on or after July 1, 2023, where a dairy product is used by the purchaser as an ingredient or component in the manufacturing in Washington of a dairy product;
(d)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2035, fruits or vegetables by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables, or selling at wholesale fruits or vegetables manufactured by the seller by canning, preserving, freezing, processing, or dehydrating fresh fruits or vegetables and sold to purchasers who transport in the ordinary course of business the goods out of this state; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the products manufactured or the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. Sellers must keep and preserve records for the period required by RCW
82.32.070
establishing that the goods were transported by the purchaser in the ordinary course of business out of this state.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wood biomass fuel; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is equal to the value of wood biomass fuel manufactured, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent. For the purposes of this section, &quot;wood biomass fuel&quot; means a liquid or gaseous fuel that is produced from lignocellulosic feedstocks, including wood, forest, or field residue and dedicated energy crops, and that does not include wood treated with chemical preservations such as creosote, pentachlorophenol, or copper-chrome-arsenic.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of splitting or processing dried peas; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the value of the peas split or processed, multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every nonprofit corporation and nonprofit association engaging within this state in research and development, as to such corporations and associations, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.5 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of slaughtering, breaking and/or processing perishable meat products and/or selling the same at wholesale only and not at retail; as to such persons the tax imposed is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such sales multiplied by the rate of 0.138 percent.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was $250,000 or less; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of acting as a travel agent or tour operator and whose annual taxable amount for the prior calendar year from such business was more than $250,000; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent through June 30, 2019, and 0.9 percent beginning July 1, 2019.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as an international steamship agent, international customs house broker, international freight forwarder, vessel and/or cargo charter broker in foreign commerce, and/or international air cargo agent; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to only international activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the movement of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross proceeds derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.275 percent. Persons subject to taxation under this subsection are exempt from payment of taxes imposed by chapter
82.16
RCW for that portion of their business subject to taxation under this subsection. Stevedoring and associated activities pertinent to the conduct of goods and commodities in waterborne interstate or foreign commerce are defined as all activities of a labor, service or transportation nature whereby cargo may be loaded or unloaded to or from vessels or barges, passing over, onto or under a wharf, pier, or similar structure; cargo may be moved to a warehouse or similar holding or storage yard or area to await further movement in import or export or may move to a consolidation freight station and be stuffed, unstuffed, containerized, separated or otherwise segregated or aggregated for delivery or loaded on any mode of transportation for delivery to its consignee. Specific activities included in this definition are: Wharfage, handling, loading, unloading, moving of cargo to a convenient place of delivery to the consignee or a convenient place for further movement to export mode; documentation services in connection with the receipt, delivery, checking, care, custody and control of cargo required in the transfer of cargo; imported automobile handling prior to delivery to consignee; terminal stevedoring and incidental vessel services, including but not limited to plugging and unplugging refrigerator service to containers, trailers, and other refrigerated cargo receptacles, and securing ship hatch covers.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of disposing of low-level waste, as defined in RCW
70A.380.010
; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to such business is equal to the gross income of the business, excluding any fees imposed under chapter
70A.384
RCW, multiplied by the rate of 3.3 percent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the gross income of the taxpayer is attributable to activities both within and without this state, the gross income attributable to this state must be determined in accordance with the methods of apportionment required under RCW
82.04.460
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state as an insurance producer licensed under chapter
48.17
RCW or a surplus line broker licensed under chapter
48.15
RCW; as to such persons, the amount of the tax with respect to such licensed activities is equal to the gross income of such business multiplied by the rate of 0.5 percent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in business as a hospital, as defined in chapter
70.41
RCW, that is operated as a nonprofit corporation or by the state or any of its political subdivisions, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.75 percent through June 30, 1995, and 1.5 percent thereafter.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning October 1, 2005, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing commercial airplanes, or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.4235 percent from October 1, 2005, through June 30, 2007;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>0.2904 percent beginning July 1, 2007, through March 31, 2020; and
(iii)(A) Beginning April 1, 2020, through December 31, 2026, 0.484 percent, subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies to all business activities described in this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies to all business activities described in this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning July 1, 2008, upon every person who is not eligible to report under the provisions of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_10__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and is engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes, or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of such tooling manufactured by the seller, as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to such business is, in the case of manufacturers, equal to the value of the product manufactured and the gross proceeds of sales of the product manufactured, or in the case of processors for hire, be equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>0.2904 percent through March 31, 2020;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning April 1, 2020, the following rates, which are subject to any reduction required under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>on the business of making retail sales of tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes; and
(B) 0.484 percent on all other business activities described in this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>on the business of making retail sales of tooling specifically designed for use in manufacturing commercial airplanes or components of such airplanes; and
(B) 0.5 percent on all other business activities described in this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to all other requirements under this title, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
. However, this requirement does not apply to persons reporting under the tax rate in (a)(iii) of this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and 0.484 percent, respectively.
(ii) Nothing in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed as affecting the obligation of a person reporting under a tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
: (A) Pursuant to another provision of this title as a result of claiming a tax credit or exemption; or (B) pursuant to</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>as a result of claiming the tax rates in</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for periods ending before April 1, 2020.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After March 31, 2021, the tax rates under (a)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must be reduced to 0.357 percent provided the conditions in RCW
82.04.2602
are met. The effective date of the rates authorized under this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>must occur on the first day of the next calendar quarter that is at least 60 days after the department receives the last of the two written notices pursuant to RCW
82.04.2602</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>are subject to the aerospace apprenticeship utilization rates required under RCW
49.04.220
by April 1, 2026, or five years after the effective date of the 0.357 percent rate authorized under this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_e__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of RCW
82.32.805
and
82.32.808
do not apply to this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in (f)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1, 2040.
(ii) With respect to the manufacturing of commercial airplanes or making sales, at retail or wholesale, of commercial airplanes, this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>does not apply on and after July 1st of the year in which the department makes a determination that any final assembly or wing assembly of any version or variant of a commercial airplane that is the basis of a siting of a significant commercial airplane manufacturing program in the state under RCW
82.32.850
has been sited outside the state of Washington. This subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this subsection, &quot;a significant commercial airplane manufacturer&quot; means a manufacturer of commercial airplanes with at least 50,000 full-time employees in Washington as of January 1, 2021.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of extracting timber or extracting for hire timber; as to such persons the amount of tax with respect to the business is, in the case of extractors, equal to the value of products, including by-products, extracted, or in the case of extractors for hire, equal to the gross income of the business, multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of manufacturing or processing for hire:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber into timber products or wood products;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products into other timber products or wood products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling at wholesale:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Timber extracted by that person;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>timber products manufactured by that person from timber or other timber products;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>wood products manufactured by that person from timber or timber products; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_11__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>manufactured by that person; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross proceeds of sales of the timber, timber products, wood products, or products defined in RCW
19.27.570</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>multiplied by the rate of 0.4235 percent from July 1, 2006, through June 30, 2007, and 0.2904 percent from July 1, 2007, through June 30, 2045.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until July 1, 2045, upon every person engaging within this state in the business of selling standing timber; as to such persons the amount of the tax with respect to the business is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.2904 percent. For purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this subsection, the following definitions apply:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Biocomposite surface products&quot; means surface material products containing, by weight or volume, more than 50 percent recycled paper and that also use nonpetroleum-based phenolic resin as a bonding agent.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Paper and paper products&quot; means products made of interwoven cellulosic fibers held together largely by hydrogen bonding. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; includes newsprint; office, printing, fine, and pressure-sensitive papers; paper napkins, towels, and toilet tissue; kraft bag, construction, and other kraft industrial papers; paperboard, liquid packaging containers, containerboard, corrugated, and solid-fiber containers including linerboard and corrugated medium; and related types of cellulosic products containing primarily, by weight or volume, cellulosic materials. &quot;Paper and paper products&quot; does not include books, newspapers, magazines, periodicals, and other printed publications, advertising materials, calendars, and similar types of printed materials.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Recycled paper&quot; means paper and paper products having 50 percent or more of their fiber content that comes from postconsumer waste. For purposes of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Timber&quot; means forest trees, standing or down, on privately or publicly owned land. &quot;Timber&quot; does not include Christmas trees that are cultivated by agricultural methods or short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Timber products&quot; means:
(A) Logs, wood chips, sawdust, wood waste, and similar products obtained wholly from the processing of timber, short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, or both;
(B) Pulp, including market pulp and pulp derived from recovered paper or paper products; and
(C) Recycled paper, but only when used in the manufacture of biocomposite surface products.
(vi) &quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_v__subsec_vi">
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Wood products&quot; means paper and paper products; dimensional lumber; engineered wood products such as particleboard, oriented strand board, medium density fiberboard, and plywood; wood doors; wood windows; and biocomposite surface products.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_f">
            <num>(f)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except for small harvesters as defined in RCW
84.33.035
, a person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may be construed to affect the taxation of any activity defined as a retail sale in RCW
82.04.050</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or (c), defined as a wholesale sale in RCW
82.04.060</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in inspecting, testing, labeling, and storing canned salmon owned by another person, as to such persons, the amount of tax with respect to such activities is equal to the gross income derived from such activities multiplied by the rate of 0.5 percent.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_13__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon every person engaging within this state in the business of printing a newspaper, publishing a newspaper, or both, the amount of tax on such business is equal to the gross income of the business multiplied by the rate of 0.35 percent until July 1, 2024, and 0.5 percent thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_13__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person reporting under the tax rate provided in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
.
[
2025 c 423 s 102
;
2025 c 420 s 113
. Prior:
2023 c 422 s 5
;
2023 c 286 s 3
;
2022 c 16 s 140
;
2021 c 145 s 7
;
2020 c 165 s 3
; prior:
2019 c 425 s 1
;
2019 c 336 s 4
;
2018 c 164 s 3
;
2017 c 135 s 11
; prior:
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 602
;
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 205
; prior:
2014 c 140 s 6
; (2014 c 140 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2014 c 140 s 4
; (2014 c 140 s 3 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6
; (2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5 expired July 1, 2015);
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203
; (2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202 expired July 1, 2015); prior: (2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 602 expired July 1, 2015);
2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 204
;
2011 c 2 s 203
(Initiative Measure No. 1107, approved November 2, 2010);
2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 506
; (2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 505 expired June 10, 2010);
2010 c 114 s 107
; prior:
2009 c 479 s 64
;
2009 c 461 s 1
;
2009 c 162 s 34
; prior:
2008 c 296 s 1
;
2008 c 217 s 100
;
2008 c 81 s 4
; prior:
2007 c 54 s 6
;
2007 c 48 s 2
; prior:
2006 c 354 s 4
;
2006 c 300 s 1
; prior:
2005 c 513 s 2
;
2005 c 443 s 4
; prior:
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 4
;
2003 2nd sp.s. c 1 s 3
;
2003 c 339 s 11
;
2003 c 261 s 11
;
2001 2nd sp.s. c 25 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 312 s 5
;
1998 c 311 s 2
; prior:
1998 c 170 s 4
;
1996 c 148 s 2
;
1996 c 115 s 1
; prior:
1995 2nd sp.s. c 12 s 1
;
1995 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 1
;
1993 sp.s. c 25 s 104
;
1993 c 492 s 304
;
1991 c 272 s 15
;
1990 c 21 s 2
;
1987 c 139 s 1
; prior:
1985 c 471 s 1
;
1985 c 135 s 2
;
1983 2nd ex.s. c 3 s 5
; prior:
1983 1st ex.s. c 66 s 4
;
1983 1st ex.s. c 55 s 4
;
1982 2nd ex.s. c 13 s 1
;
1982 c 10 s 16
; prior:
1981 c 178 s 1
;
1981 c 172 s 3
;
1979 ex.s. c 196 s 2
;
1975 1st ex.s. c 291 s 7
;
1971 ex.s. c 281 s 5
;
1971 ex.s. c 186 s 3
;
1969 ex.s. c 262 s 36
;
1967 ex.s. c 149 s 10
;
1965 ex.s. c 173 s 6
;
1961 c 15 s 82.04.260
; prior:
1959 c 211 s 2
;
1955 c 389 s 46
; prior:
1953 c 91 s 4
;
1951 2nd ex.s. c 28 s 4
; 1950 ex.s. c </p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>RCW
82.04.280
was amended by 2025 c 9 s 2, changing subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section was amended by 2025 c 420 s 113 and by 2025 c 423 s 102, each without reference to the other. Both amendments are incorporated in the publication of this section under RCW
1.12.025</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that, according to the most recent tax exemption study published by the department of revenue, there are currently 786 tax exemptions for the major state and local tax sources in Washington. The exemptions result in nearly $200,000,000,000 of taxpayer savings for the current biennium. The legislature acknowledges that certain tax preferences, such as the sales and use tax exemption for food and the working families tax credit, are intended to rebalance Washington's tax code for working people. However, the legislature further acknowledges that many existing tax preferences are the result of private interests securing preferential tax treatment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For that reason, the legislature enacted robust tax preference performance measures to create greater tax preference transparency and accountability and provide a framework for legislators to make informed decisions on the most efficient use of taxpayer dollars. To ensure tax exemptions meet certain public policy objectives, the joint legislative audit and review committee, a nonpartisan legislative agency, routinely evaluates tax preferences based on specific criteria provided in law and reports that information to the legislature each year. The reports provide accurate, comprehensive, unbiased data that policymakers may use to determine if a tax preference should be continued, modified, or repealed. Additionally, the citizen commission for performance measurement of tax preferences is responsible for selecting which tax preferences are reviewed each year and provides comment on the legislative auditor's reports. Both entities provide recommendations to the legislature on the effectiveness of a tax preference in meeting certain performance measures.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Furthermore, the department of revenue assists in the tax preference evaluation process by collecting data from taxpayer beneficiaries and regularly reviewing changes in state and federal law. The analysis by the department and legislative auditor often reveals that a tax exemption is legally obsolete, meaning the specific legal conditions that existed when the exemption was enacted have since changed and the original legislative intent is no longer applicable. Additionally, some tax exemptions are simply not used and should be removed from the tax code to create better clarity for taxpayers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature recognizes that more progress is needed for the state to have a fair and balanced tax system that provides sustainable and ample funding for public schools, health care, and other programs that protect the safety and well-being of the public, as well as social services that provide critical, basic-needs assistance for our state's most vulnerable residents. The legislature further recognizes that the tax preference performance review process provides an opportunity for policymakers to evaluate the tax code to ensure the state is not losing essential revenue due to inefficient or no longer applicable tax exemptions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Thus, the legislature intends to enact recommendations from the joint legislative audit and review committee, the citizen commission for performance measurement of tax preferences, and the department of revenue, including eliminating several obsolete tax preferences, clarifying legislative intent to better inform future tax preference performance reviews, adding expiration dates, and other actions aimed at creating a fair and balanced tax system.&quot; [
2025 c 423 s 1
.]
Necessity of act
—
2025 c 423:
&quot;This act is necessary for the support of the state government and its existing public institutions.&quot; [
2025 c 423 s 402
.]
Effective date
—
2025 c 420 s 113:
&quot;Section 113 of this act takes effect January 1, 2034.&quot; [
2025 c 420 s 505
.]
Tax preference performance statement exemption
—
Automatic expiration date exemption
—
Necessity of act
—
2025 c 420:
See notes following RCW
82.04.230
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
2023 c 422 ss 2-5:
See note following RCW
82.04.4268
.
Intent
—
Finding
—
2022 c 16:
See note following RCW
69.50.101
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
Effective date
—
2020 c 165:
See notes following RCW
82.04.2602
.
Effective date
—
2019 c 425:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 2019.&quot; [
2019 c 425 s 2
.]
Findings
—
Intent
—
2019 c 336:
See notes following RCW
82.04.261
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
Effective date
—
2018 c 164:
See notes following RCW
82.08.900
.
Effective date
—
2017 c 135:
See note following RCW
82.32.534
.
Expiration date
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6; 2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 602:
&quot;Section 602 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 603
;
2012 2nd sp.s. c 6 s 704
.]
Findings
—
Intent
—
Tax preference performance statement
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 602:
&quot;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that over the last fifteen years, technological transformation and other developments have radically changed the newspaper industry business model, which remains in transition. The legislature further finds that the economic hardship wrought by this digital transformation has been substantial. The legislature finds that a strong and vibrant newspaper industry in Washington is beneficial to the state's citizens and to the conduct of good government at every level. The legislature further finds that advertising revenue of all United States newspapers fell from 63.5 billion dollars in 2000 to about twenty-three billion dollars in 2013, and is still falling. The legislature further finds that traditional news organizations' ability to support high quality news gathering and reporting relied primarily on a model in which advertisers paid to reach mass audiences attracted by newspapers. The legislature further finds that advertisers found it advantageous to pay to reach a mass audience because other advertising mediums were limited and less effective. The digital era has greatly fractured traditional spending by advertisers and turned this model on its head such that newspapers continue to require time to adapt so they may continue their public service mission. The legislature also finds that the business and occupation tax rate for the newspaper industry was pegged to the general manufacturing and wholesaling rate from 1937 until 2009, when the legislature extended tax relief to the industry due to this shift. It is the legislature's intent to extend this tax relief to the industry until its revenues and business model have stabilized. It is the legislature's further intent to provide a uniform tax rate for the industry to minimize the burden of reporting state business and occupation taxes for different types of revenue, which oftentimes are impossible to account for separately by the taxpayer.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This subsection is the tax preference performance statement for the newspaper tax preferences in section 602 of this act. The performance statement is only intended to be used for subsequent evaluation of the tax preference. It is not intended to create a private right of action by any party or be used to determine eligibility for preferential tax treatment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The legislature categorizes this tax preference as one intended to provide temporary tax relief as described in RCW
82.32.808</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It is the legislature's specific public policy objective to provide business and occupation tax relief to the newspaper industry as it continues to adjust to significant revenue shifts and technological changes. As a secondary public policy objective, it is the legislature's intent to provide a permanent uniform rate for the industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To measure the effectiveness of the preference provided in this act in achieving the specific public policy objective described in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee must evaluate year-to-year changes in gross revenue derived from all sources for newspaper firms claiming the preferential tax rate under RCW
82.04.260</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The information provided in the annual tax preference accountability report submitted by taxpayers as required by the department of revenue and taxpayer data provided by the department of revenue is intended to provide the informational basis for the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the data source described under</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the joint legislative audit and review committee may use any other data it deems necessary in performing the evaluation under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_260__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 601
.]
Effective dates
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 ss 202-205:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Contingent effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 6:
&quot;Section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 39
.]
Contingent expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 5:
&quot;Section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015, subject to the contingency stated in section 2, chapter 2, Laws of 2013 3rd sp. sess.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 38
.]
Effective date
—
2014 c 140 s 4:
&quot;Section 4 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 37
.]
Expiration date
—
2014 c 140 s 3:
&quot;Section 3 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2014 c 140 s 36
.]
Effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 6:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 16
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 5:
&quot;Subject to section 2 of this act, section 5 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2 s 15
.]
Contingent effective date
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See RCW
82.32.850
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
2013 3rd sp.s. c 2:
See note following RCW
82.32.850
.
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 203:
&quot;Section 203 of this act takes effect July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1902
.]
Expiration date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 202:
&quot;Section 202 of this act expires July 1, 2015.&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13 s 1901
.]
Intent
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 13:
&quot;The intent of part II of this act is to incentivize the creation of additional jobs in Washington in the dairy industry and related industries that manufacture dairy-based products. More specifically, it is the intent of part II of this act to encourage infant formula producers to locate new facilities in Washington or expand existing facilities in Washington through an extension of a preferential business and occupation tax </p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
