<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.298"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.298"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.298/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.298/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.298/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.298/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_04_298">
        <num>RCW 82.04.298</num>
        <heading>Tax on qualified grocery distribution cooperatives</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of tax with respect to a qualified grocery distribution cooperative's sales of groceries or related goods for resale, excluding items subject to tax under RCW
82.04.260</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A qualified grocery distribution cooperative is allowed a deduction from the gross proceeds of sales of groceries or related goods for resale, excluding items subject to tax under RCW
82.04.260</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The definitions in this subsection apply throughout this section unless the context clearly requires otherwise.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Grocery distribution cooperative&quot; means an entity that sells groceries and related items to customer-owners of the grocery distribution cooperative and has customer-owners, in the aggregate, who own a majority of the outstanding ownership interests of the grocery distribution cooperative or of the entity controlling the grocery distribution cooperative. &quot;Grocery distribution cooperative&quot; includes an entity that controls a grocery distribution cooperative.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Qualified grocery distribution cooperative&quot; means:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A grocery distribution cooperative that has been determined by a court of record of the state of Washington to be not engaged in wholesaling or making sales at wholesale, within the meaning of RCW
82.04.270
or any similar provision of a municipal ordinance that imposes a tax on gross receipts, gross proceeds of sales, or gross income, with respect to purchases made by customer-owners, and subsequently changes its form of doing business to make sales at wholesale of groceries or related items to its customer-owners; or</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grocery distribution cooperative that has acquired substantially all of the assets of a grocery distribution cooperative described in</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Customer-owner&quot; means a person who has an ownership interest in a grocery distribution cooperative and purchases groceries and related items at wholesale from that grocery distribution cooperative.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Controlling&quot; means holding fifty percent or more of the voting interests of an entity and having at least equal power to direct or cause the direction of the management and policies of the entity, whether through the ownership of voting securities, by contract, or otherwise.
[
2011 c 2 s 204
(Initiative Measure No. 1107, approved November 2, 2010);
2010 1st sp.s. c 23 s 511
;
2008 c 49 s 1
;
2001 1st sp.s. c 9 s 1
.]
NOTES:
Findings
—
Construction
—
2011 c 2 (Initiative Measure No. 1107):
See notes following RCW
82.08.0293
.
Effective date
—
2010 1st sp.s. c 23:
See note following RCW
82.04.4292
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
2010 1st sp.s. c 23:
See notes following RCW
82.04.220
.
Effective dates
—
2001 1st sp.s. c 9:
&quot;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Sections 1, 2, 4, and 8 of this act are necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and take effect immediately [June 11, 2001].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Sections 3 and 5 of this act are necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and take effect July 1, 2001.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Section 6 of this act takes effect July 1, 2003.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_298__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Section 7 [of this act] is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 22, 2001.&quot; [
2001 1st sp.s. c 9 s 9
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
