<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.033"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.033"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.033/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.033/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.033/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.033/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_32_033">
        <num>RCW 82.32.033</num>
        <heading>Registration certificates—Special events—Promoter's duties—Penalties—Definitions</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A promoter of a special event within the state of Washington shall not permit a vendor to make or solicit retail sales of tangible personal property or services at the special event unless the promoter makes a good faith effort to obtain verification that the vendor has obtained a certificate of registration from the department.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A promoter of a special event shall:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Keep, in addition to the records required under RCW
82.32.070
, a record of the dates and place of each special event, and the name, address, and registration certificate number of each vendor permitted to make or solicit retail sales of tangible personal property or services at the special event. The record of the date and place of a special event, and the name, address, and registration certificate number of each vendor at the event shall be preserved for a period of one year from the date of a special event; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Provide to the department, within twenty days of receipt of a written request from the department, a list of vendors permitted to make or solicit retail sales of tangible personal property or services. The list shall be in a form and contain such information as the department may require, and shall include the date and place of the event, and the name, address, and registration certificate number of each vendor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a promoter fails to make a good faith effort to comply with the provisions of this section, the promoter is liable for the penalties provided in this subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a promoter fails to make a good faith effort to comply with the provisions of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, the department shall impose a penalty of one hundred dollars for each vendor permitted to make or solicit retail sales of tangible personal property or services at the special event.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a promoter fails to make a good faith effort to comply with the provisions of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the department shall impose a penalty of:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Two hundred fifty dollars if the information requested is not received by the department within twenty days of the department's written request; and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One hundred dollars for each vendor for whom the information as required by subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section is not provided to the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The aggregate of penalties imposed under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section may not exceed two thousand five hundred dollars for a special event if the promoter has not previously been penalized under this section. Under no circumstances is a promoter liable for sales tax or business and occupation tax not remitted to the department by a vendor at a special event.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department shall notify a promoter by mail, or electronically as provided in RCW
82.32.135
, of any penalty imposed under this section, and the penalty shall be due within thirty days from the date of the notice. If any penalty imposed under this section is not received by the department by the due date, there shall be assessed interest on the unpaid amount beginning the day following the due date until the penalty is paid in full. The rate of interest shall be computed on a daily basis on the amount of outstanding penalty at the rate as computed under RCW
82.32.050</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For purposes of this section:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_6__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Promoter&quot; means a person who organizes, operates, or sponsors a special event and who contracts with vendors for participation in the special event.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_6__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Special event&quot; means an entertainment, amusement, recreational, educational, or marketing event, whether held on a regular or irregular basis, at which more than one vendor makes or solicits retail sales of tangible personal property or services. The term includes, but is not limited to: Auto shows, recreational vehicle shows, boat shows, home shows, garden shows, hunting and fishing shows, stamp shows, comic book shows, sports memorabilia shows, craft shows, art shows, antique shows, flea markets, exhibitions, festivals, concerts, swap meets, bazaars, carnivals, athletic contests, circuses, fairs, or other similar activities. &quot;Special event&quot; does not include an event that is organized for the exclusive benefit of any nonprofit organization as defined in RCW
82.04.3651
. An event is organized for the exclusive benefit of a nonprofit organization if all of the gross proceeds of retail sales of all vendors at the event inure to the benefit of the nonprofit organization on whose behalf the event is being held. &quot;Special event&quot; does not include athletic contests that involve competition between teams, when such competition consists of more than five contests in a calendar year by at least one team at the same facility or site.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_6__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Vendor&quot; means a person who, at a special event, makes or solicits retail sales of tangible personal property or services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Good faith effort to comply&quot; and &quot;good faith effort to obtain&quot; may be shown by, but is not limited to, circumstances where a promoter:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Includes a statement on all written contracts with its vendors that a valid registration certificate number issued by the department of revenue is required for participation in the special event and requires vendors to indicate their registration certificate number on these contracts; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Provides the department with a list of vendors and their associated registration certificate numbers as provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section does not apply to:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_8__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A special event whose promoter does not charge more than two hundred dollars for a vendor to participate in a special event;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_8__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A special event whose promoter charges a percentage of sales instead of, or in addition to, a flat charge for a vendor to participate in a special event if the promoter, in good faith, believes that no vendor will pay more than two hundred dollars to participate in the special event; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_033__subsec_8__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person who does not organize, operate, or sponsor a special event, but only provides a venue, supplies, furnishings, fixtures, equipment, or services to a promoter of a special event.
[
2007 c 111 s 105
;
2004 c 253 s 1
;
2003 1st sp.s. c 13 s 15
.]
NOTES:
Part headings not law
—
2007 c 111:
See note following RCW
82.16.120
.
Effective dates
—
2003 1st sp.s. c 13:
See note following RCW
82.32.045
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
