<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.060"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.060"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.060/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.060/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.060/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.060/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_32_060">
        <num>RCW 82.32.060</num>
        <heading>Excess payment of tax, penalty, or interest—Credit or refund—Payment of judgments for refund</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, upon receipt of an application by a taxpayer for a refund or for an audit of the taxpayer's records, or upon an examination of the returns or records of any taxpayer, it is determined by the department that within the statutory period for assessment of taxes, penalties, or interest prescribed by RCW
82.32.050
any amount of tax, penalty, or interest has been paid in excess of that properly due, the excess amount paid within, or attributable to, such period must be credited to the taxpayer's account or must be refunded to the taxpayer, at the taxpayer's option. Except as provided in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, no refund or credit may be made for taxes, penalties, or interest paid more than four years prior to the beginning of the calendar year in which the refund application is made or examination of records is completed.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The execution of a written waiver under RCW
82.32.050
or
82.32.100
will extend the time for making a refund or credit of any taxes paid during, or attributable to, the years covered by the waiver if, prior to the expiration of the waiver period, an application for refund of such taxes is made by the taxpayer or the department discovers a refund or credit is due.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A refund or credit must be allowed for an excess payment resulting from the failure to claim a bad debt deduction, credit, or refund under RCW
82.04.4284
,
82.08.037
,
82.12.037
,
82.14B.150
, or
82.16.050</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for debts that became bad debts under 26 U.S.C. Sec. 166, as amended or renumbered as of January 1, 2003, less than four years prior to the beginning of the calendar year in which the refund application is made or examination of records is completed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any such refunds must be made by means of vouchers approved by the department and by the issuance of state warrants drawn upon and payable from such funds as the legislature may provide. However, taxpayers who are required to pay taxes by electronic funds transfer under RCW
82.32.080
must have any refunds paid by electronic funds transfer if the department has the necessary account information to facilitate a refund by electronic funds transfer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any judgment for which a recovery is granted by any court of competent jurisdiction, not appealed from, for tax, penalties, and interest which were paid by the taxpayer, and costs, in a suit by any taxpayer must be paid in the same manner, as provided in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, upon the filing with the department of a certified copy of the order or judgment of the court.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Interest at the rate of three percent per annum must be allowed by the department and by any court on the amount of any refund, credit, or other recovery allowed to a taxpayer for taxes, penalties, or interest paid by the taxpayer before January 1, 1992. This rate of interest applies for all interest allowed through December 31, 1998. Interest allowed after December 31, 1998, must be computed at the rate as computed under RCW
82.32.050</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For refunds or credits of amounts paid or other recovery allowed to a taxpayer after December 31, 1991, the rate of interest must be the rate as computed for assessments under RCW
82.32.050</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>less one percent. This rate of interest applies for all interest allowed through December 31, 1998. Interest allowed after December 31, 1998, must be computed at the rate as computed under RCW
82.32.050</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Interest allowed on a credit notice or refund issued after December 31, 2003, must be computed as follows:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_5__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If all overpayments for each calendar year and all reporting periods ending with the final month included in a notice or refund were made on or before the due date of the final return for each calendar year or the final reporting period included in the notice or refund:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_5__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Interest must be computed from January 31st following each calendar year included in a notice or refund;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_5__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Interest must be computed from the last day of the month following the final month included in a notice or refund; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_5__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For interest associated with annual tax reporting periods having a due date as prescribed in RCW
82.32.045</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and
82.87.110
, interest must be computed from the last day of April following each such annual reporting period included in a notice or refund.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the taxpayer has not made all overpayments for each calendar year and all reporting periods ending with the final month included in a notice or refund on or before the dates specified by RCW
82.32.045
for the final return for each calendar year or the final month included in the notice or refund, interest must be computed from the last day of the month following the date on which payment in full of the liabilities was made for each calendar year included in a notice or refund, and the last day of the month following the date on which payment in full of the liabilities was made if the final month included in a notice or refund is not the end of a calendar year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_060__subsec_3__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Interest included in a credit notice must accrue up to the date the taxpayer could reasonably be expected to use the credit notice, as defined by the department's rules. If a credit notice is converted to a refund, interest must be recomputed to the date the refund is issued, but not to exceed the amount of interest that would have been allowed with the credit notice.
[
2025 c 409 s 13
;
2020 c 139 s 61
;
2009 c 176 s 4
;
2004 c 153 s 306
;
2003 c 73 s 2
;
1999 c 358 s 13
;
1997 c 157 s 2
;
1992 c 169 s 2
;
1991 c 142 s 10
;
1990 c 69 s 1
;
1989 c 378 s 20
;
1979 ex.s. c 95 s 4
;
1971 ex.s. c 299 s 17
;
1965 ex.s. c 173 s 27
;
1963 c 22 s 1
;
1961 c 15 s 82.32.060
. Prior:
1951 1st ex.s. c 9 s 6
;
1949 c 228 s 21
;
1935 c 180 s 189
; Rem. Supp. 1949 s 8370-189.]
NOTES:
Retroactive application
—
Effective date
—
2020 c 139 ss 60-62:
See notes following RCW
82.32.050
.
Retroactive effective date
—
Effective date
—
2004 c 153:
See note following RCW
82.08.0293
.
Effective date
—
2003 c 73 s 2:
&quot;Section 2 of this act takes effect January 1, 2004.&quot; [
2003 c 73 s 3
.]
Effective date
—
1999 c 358 ss 1 and 3-21:
See note following RCW
82.04.3651
.
Effective date
—
Applicability
—
1992 c 169:
See note following RCW
82.32.050
.
Effective date
—
1991 c 142 ss 9-11:
See note following RCW
82.32.050
.
Effective date
—
1990 c 69:
&quot;This act shall take effect January 1, 1991.&quot; [
1990 c 69 s 5
.]
Severability
—
1990 c 69:
&quot;If any provision of this act or its application to any person or circumstance is held invalid, the remainder of the act or the application of the provision to other persons or circumstances is not affected.&quot; [
1990 c 69 s 4
.]
Effective dates
—
Severability
—
1971 ex.s. c 299:
See notes following RCW
82.04.050
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
