<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.030"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.030"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.030/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.030/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.030/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.030/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_32_030">
        <num>RCW 82.32.030</num>
        <heading>Registration certificates—Threshold levels—Central registration system</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Except as provided in subsections</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, if any person engages in any business or performs any act upon which a tax is imposed by the preceding chapters, he or she must, under such rules as the department prescribes, apply for and obtain from the department a registration certificate. Such registration certificate is personal and nontransferable and is valid as long as the taxpayer continues in business and pays the tax accrued to the state. In case business is transacted at two or more separate places by one taxpayer, a separate registration certificate for each place at which business is transacted with the public is required. Each certificate must be numbered and must show the name, residence, and place and character of business of the taxpayer and such other information as the department of revenue deems necessary and must be posted in a conspicuous place at the place of business for which it is issued. Where a place of business of the taxpayer is changed, the taxpayer must return to the department the existing certificate, and a new certificate will be issued for the new place of business. No person required to be registered under this section may engage in any business taxable hereunder without first being so registered. The department, by rule, may provide for the issuance of certificates of registration to temporary places of business.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the person is a dealer as defined in RCW
9.41.010
, registration under this section is not required if the following conditions are met:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person's value of products, gross proceeds of sales, or gross income of the business, from all business activities taxable under chapter
82.04
RCW, is less than twelve thousand dollars per year;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The person's gross income of the business from all activities taxable under chapter
82.16
RCW is less than twelve thousand dollars per year;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The person is not required to collect or pay to the department of revenue any other tax or fee that the department is authorized to collect; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_2__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The person is not otherwise required to obtain a license subject to the business license application procedure provided in chapter
19.02
RCW.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All persons who agree to collect and remit sales and use tax to the department under the agreement must register through the central registration system authorized under the agreement. Persons required to register under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section are not relieved of that requirement because of registration under this subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Persons registered under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section who are not required to register under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_030__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section and who are not otherwise subject to the requirements of chapter
19.02
RCW are not subject to the fees imposed by the department under the authority of RCW
19.02.075
.
[
2017 c 323 s 505
;
2011 c 298 s 38
;
2007 c 6 s 202
;
1996 c 111 s 2
. Prior:
1994 sp.s. c 7 s 446
;
1994 sp.s. c 2 s 2
;
1992 c 206 s 8
;
1982 1st ex.s. c 4 s 1
;
1979 ex.s. c 95 s 1
;
1975 1st ex.s. c 278 s 77
;
1961 c 15 s 82.32.030
; prior: 1941 c 178 s 19, part; 1937 c 227 s 16, part; 1935 c 180 s 187, part; Rem. Supp. 1941 s 8370-187, part.]
NOTES:
Tax preference performance statement exemption
—
Automatic expiration date exemption
—
2017 c 323:
See note following RCW
82.04.040
.
Purpose
—
Intent
—
Agency transfer
—
Contracting
—
Effective date
—
2011 c 298:
See notes following RCW
19.02.020
.
Part headings not law
—
Savings
—
Effective date
—
Severability
—
2007 c 6:
See notes following RCW
82.32.020
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
2007 c 6:
See note following RCW
82.14.390
.
Findings
—
Purpose
—
1996 c 111:
&quot;The legislature finds that small businesses play a vital role in the state's current and future economic health. The legislature also finds that the state's excise tax reporting and registration requirements are unduly burdensome for small businesses incurring little or no tax liability. The legislature recognizes the costs associated in complying with the reporting and registration requirements that are hindering the further development of those businesses. For these reasons the legislature with this act simplifies the tax reporting and registration requirements for certain small businesses.&quot; [
1996 c 111 s 1
.]
Effective date
—
1996 c 111:
&quot;This act shall take effect July 1, 1996.&quot; [
1996 c 111 s 5
.]
Finding
—
Intent
—
Severability
—
1994 sp.s. c 7:
See notes following RCW
43.70.540
.
Effective date
—
1994 sp.s. c 7 ss 401-410, 413-416, 418-437, and 439-460:
See note following RCW
9.41.010
.
Effective date
—
1994 sp.s. c 2:
See note following RCW
82.04.4451
.
Effective date
—
19</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
