<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.080"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.080"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.080/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.080/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.080/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.080/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_32_080">
        <num>RCW 82.32.080</num>
        <heading>Payment by check—Electronic funds transfer—Rules—Mailing returns or remittances—Time extension—Deposits—Time extension during state of emergency—Records—Payment must accompany return</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When authorized by the department, payment of the tax may be made by uncertified check under such rules as the department prescribes, but, if a check so received is not paid by the bank on which it is drawn, the taxpayer, by whom such check is tendered, will remain liable for payment of the tax and for all legal penalties and interest, the same as if such check had not been tendered.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, payment of the tax must be made by electronic funds transfer, as defined in RCW
82.32.085
. As an alternative to electronic funds transfer, the department may authorize other forms of electronic payment, such as payment by credit card. All taxes administered by this chapter are subject to this requirement, except that the department may exclude any taxes not reported on the combined excise tax return or any successor return from the electronic payment requirement in this subsection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may waive the electronic payment requirement in this subsection for any taxpayer or class of taxpayers, for good cause or for whom the department has assigned a reporting frequency that is less than quarterly. In the discretion of the department, a waiver under this subsection may be made temporary or permanent, and may be made on the department's own motion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department is authorized to accept payment of taxes by electronic funds transfer or other acceptable forms of electronic payment from taxpayers that are not subject to the mandatory electronic payment requirements in this subsection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, returns must be filed electronically using the department's online tax filing service or other method of electronic reporting as the department may authorize.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department may waive the electronic filing requirement in this subsection for any taxpayer or class of taxpayers, for good cause or for whom the department has assigned a reporting frequency that is less than quarterly. In the discretion of the department, a waiver under this subsection may be made temporary or permanent, and may be made on the department's own motion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department is authorized to allow electronic filing of returns from taxpayers that are not subject to the mandatory electronic filing requirements in this subsection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department, for good cause shown, may extend the time for making and filing any return, and may grant such reasonable additional time within which to make and file returns as it may deem proper, but any permanent extension granting the taxpayer a reporting date without penalty more than ten days beyond the due date, and any extension in excess of thirty days must be conditional on deposit with the department of an amount to be determined by the department which is approximately equal to the estimated tax liability for the reporting period or periods for which the extension is granted. In the case of a permanent extension or a temporary extension of more than thirty days the deposit must be deposited within the state treasury with other tax funds and a credit recorded to the taxpayer's account which may be applied to taxpayer's liability upon cancellation of the permanent extension or upon reporting of the tax liability where an extension of more than thirty days has been granted.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department must review the requirement for deposit at least annually and may require a change in the amount of the deposit required when it believes that such amount does not approximate the tax liability for the reporting period or periods for which the extension is granted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>During a state of emergency declared under RCW
43.06.010</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The department must keep full and accurate records of all funds received and disbursed by it. Subject to the provisions of RCW
82.32.105
,
82.32.052
, and
82.32.350
, the department must apply the payment of the taxpayer in the following order, without regard to any direction of the taxpayer:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Interest;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>penalties;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>fees that are not within the definition of tax in RCW
82.32.020
;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>other nontax amounts;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>taxes, except spirits taxes; and (vi) spirits taxes.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_v__subsec_vi">
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <content>
                <p>spirits taxes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this subsection, &quot;spirits taxes&quot; has the same meaning as in RCW
82.08.155
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department may refuse to accept any return that is not accompanied by a remittance of the tax shown to be due thereon or that is not filed electronically as required in this section. When such return is not accepted, the taxpayer is deemed to have failed or refused to file a return and is subject to the procedures provided in RCW
82.32.100
and to the penalties provided in RCW
82.32.090
. The above authority to refuse to accept a return may not apply when a return is timely filed electronically and a timely payment has been made by electronic funds transfer or other form of electronic payment as authorized by the department.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Except for returns and remittances required to be transmitted to the department electronically under this section and except as otherwise provided in this chapter, a return or remittance that is transmitted to the department by United States mail is deemed filed or received on the date shown by the post office cancellation mark stamped upon the envelope containing it. A return or remittance that is transmitted to the department electronically is deemed filed or received according to procedures set forth by the department.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of subsections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, &quot;good cause&quot; means the inability of a taxpayer to comply with the requirements of subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section because:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The taxpayer does not have the equipment or software necessary to enable the taxpayer to comply with subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section;
(ii) The equipment or software necessary to enable the taxpayer to comply with subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section is not functioning properly;
(iii) The taxpayer does not have access to the internet using the taxpayer's own equipment;
(iv) The taxpayer does not have a bank account or a credit card;</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The taxpayer's bank is unable to send or receive electronic funds transfer transactions; or
(vi) Some other circumstance or condition exists that, in the department's judgment, prevents the taxpayer from complying with the requirements of subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3__subsec_v__subsec_vi">
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Some other circumstance or condition exists that, in the department's judgment, prevents the taxpayer from complying with the requirements of subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Good cause&quot; also includes any circumstance that, in the department's judgment, supports the efficient or effective administration of the tax laws of this state, including providing relief from the requirements of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section to any taxpayer that is voluntarily collecting and remitting this state's sales or use taxes on sales to Washington customers but has no legal requirement to be registered with the department.
[
2015 c 86 s 311
;
2012 c 39 s 2
. Prior:
2011 c 24 s 1
;
2010 2nd sp.s. c 2 s 2
; prior:
2010 c 111 s 304
;
2010 c 106 s 226
;
2009 c 176 s 2
;
2008 c 181 s 502
;
1999 c 357 s 3
;
1997 c 156 s 3
;
1990 c 69 s 2
;
1971 ex.s. c 299 s 18
;
1965 ex.s. c 141 s 2
;
1963 ex.s. c 28 s 6
;
1961 c 15 s 82.32.080
; prior:
1951 1st ex.s. c 9 s 8
;
1949 c 228 s 22
;
1935 c 180 s 191
; Rem. Supp. 1949 s 8370-191.]
NOTES:
Construction
—
Effective date
—
2012 c 39:
See notes following RCW
82.08.155
.
Application
—
2011 c 24:
&quot;This act applies only to tax returns and payments originally due after July 22, 2011, including tax returns and payments for tax liabilities incurred before July 22, 2011, and originally due after July 22, 2011.&quot; [
2011 c 24 s 4
.]
Effective date
—
2010 2nd sp.s. c 2:
See note following RCW
82.32.052
.
Purpose
—
Retroactive application
—
Effective date
—
2010 c 111:
See notes following RCW
82.04.050
.
Effective date
—
2010 c 106:
See note following RCW
35.102.145
.
Part headings not law
—
2008 c 181:
See note following RCW
43.06.220
.
Intent
—
Effective date
—
1999 c 357:
See notes following RCW
82.32.045
.
Severability
—
Effective date
—
1990 c 69:
See notes following RCW
82.32.060
.
Effective dates
—
Severability
—
1971 ex.s. c 299:
See notes following RCW
82.04.050
.
Findings
—
Payment of excise taxes by electronic funds transfer
—
2006 c 256: See note following RCW
82.32.045
.
Tax returns, remittances, etc., filing and receipt when transmitted by mail: RCW
1.12.070
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
