<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.535"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.535"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.535/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.535/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.535/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.535/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_04_535">
        <num>RCW 82.04.535</num>
        <heading>Gross proceeds of sales calculation for mobile telecommunications service provider</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_535__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless a mobile telecommunications service provider elects to be taxed under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_535__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, the mobile telecommunications service provider must calculate gross proceeds of sales by reporting all sales to, or sales between carriers for, customers with a place of primary use within this state, regardless of where the mobile telecommunications services originate, are received, or are billed, consistent with the mobile telecommunications sourcing act, P.L. 106-252, 4 U.S.C. Secs. 116 through 126.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_535__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A mobile telecommunications service provider may elect to calculate gross proceeds of sales by including all charges for mobile telecommunications services provided to all consumers, whether the consumers are the mobile telecommunications service provider's customers or not, if the services originate from or are received on telecommunications equipment or apparatus in this state and are billed to a person in this state.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_535__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a mobile telecommunications service provider elects to be taxed under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_535__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, the mobile telecommunications service provider must provide written notice of the election before August 1, 2002, or before the beginning date of any tax year thereafter in which it wishes to change its reporting and make this election.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_535__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department may provide, by rule, for formulary reporting as necessary to implement this section.
[
2002 c 67 s 4
.]
NOTES:
Finding
—
Effective date
—
2002 c 67:
See notes following RCW
82.04.530
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
