<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.213"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.213"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.213/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.213/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.213/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.04.213/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_04_213">
        <num>RCW 82.04.213</num>
        <heading>&quot;Agricultural product,&quot; &quot;farmer,&quot; &quot;cannabis.&quot;</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_213__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Agricultural product&quot; means any product of plant cultivation or animal husbandry including, but not limited to: A product of horticulture, grain cultivation, vermiculture, viticulture, or aquaculture as defined in RCW
15.85.020
; plantation Christmas trees; short-rotation hardwoods as defined in RCW
84.33.035
; turf; or any animal including but not limited to an animal that is a private sector cultured aquatic product as defined in RCW
15.85.020
, or a bird, or insect, or the substances obtained from such an animal including honey bee products. &quot;Agricultural product&quot; does not include cannabis, useable cannabis, or cannabis-infused products, or animals defined as pet animals under RCW
16.70.020
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_213__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Cannabis,&quot; &quot;useable cannabis,&quot; and &quot;cannabis-infused products&quot; have the same meaning as in RCW
69.50.101
.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_213__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Farmer&quot; means any person engaged in the business of growing, raising, or producing, upon the person's own lands or upon the lands in which the person has a present right of possession, any agricultural product to be sold, and the growing, raising, or producing honey bee products for sale, or providing bee pollination services, by an eligible apiarist. &quot;Farmer&quot; does not include a person growing, raising, or producing such products for the person's own consumption; a person selling any animal or substance obtained therefrom in connection with the person's business of operating a stockyard or a slaughter or packing house; or a person in respect to the business of taking, cultivating, or raising timber.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_213__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Eligible apiarist&quot; means a person who owns or keeps one or more bee colonies and who grows, raises, or produces honey bee products for sale at wholesale and is registered under RCW
15.60.021
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_04_213__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Honey bee products&quot; means queen honey bees, packaged honey bees, honey, pollen, bees wax, propolis, or other substances obtained from honey bees. &quot;Honey bee products&quot; does not include manufactured substances or articles.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_04_213__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The terms &quot;agriculture,&quot; &quot;farming,&quot; &quot;horticulture,&quot; &quot;horticultural,&quot; and &quot;horticultural product&quot; may not be construed to include or relate to cannabis, useable cannabis, or cannabis-infused products unless the applicable term is explicitly defined to include cannabis, useable cannabis, or cannabis-infused products.
[
2022 c 16 s 139
;
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 1102
;
2014 c 140 s 2
. Prior:
2001 c 118 s 2
;
2001 c 97 s 3
;
1993 sp.s. c 25 s 302
.]
NOTES:
Reviser's note:
The definitions in this section have been alphabetized pursuant to RCW
1.08.015</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
