<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.45.035"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.45.035"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.45.035/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.45.035/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.45.035/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.45.035/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_45_035">
        <num>RCW 82.45.035</num>
        <heading>Determining selling price of leases with option to purchase—Mining property—Payment, security when selling price not separately stated</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_45_035__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>at the time of termination, or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_45_035__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>at the time that all of the consideration due to the seller has been paid and the transaction is completed except for the delivery of the deed to the buyer, or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_45_035__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>at the time when the buyer unequivocally exercises an option to purchase the property, whichever of the three events occurs first.
The term &quot;mining property&quot; means property containing or believed to contain metallic minerals and sold or leased under terms which require the purchaser or lessor to conduct exploration or mining work thereon and for no other use. The term &quot;metallic minerals&quot; does not include clays, coal, sand and gravel, peat, gypsite, or stone, including limestone.
The state department of revenue shall further provide by rule for cases where the selling price is not separately stated or is not ascertainable at the time of sale, for the payment of the tax at a time when the selling price is ascertained, in which case suitable security may be required for payment of the tax, and may further provide for the determination of the selling price by an appraisal by the county assessor, based on the full and true market value, which appraisal shall be prima facie evidence of the selling price of the real property.
[
1969 ex.s. c 223 s 28A.45.035
. Prior:
1967 ex.s. c 149 s 1
;
1959 c 208 s 1
;
1951 2nd ex.s. c 19 s 3
. Formerly RCW
28A.45.035
,
28.45.035
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
