<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.150"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.150"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.150/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.150/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.150/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.150/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_60_150">
        <num>RCW 74.60.150</num>
        <heading>Conditions</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The assessment, collection, and disbursement of funds under this chapter shall be conditional upon:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Final approval by the centers for medicare and medicaid services in order to implement the applicable sections of this chapter, except under RCW
74.60.090
, including, if necessary, waiver of the broad-based or uniformity requirements as specified under section 1903(w)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To the extent necessary, amendment of contracts between the authority and managed care organizations in order to implement this chapter; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Certification by the office of financial management that appropriations have been adopted that fully support the rates established in this chapter for the upcoming calendar year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This chapter does not take effect or ceases to be imposed, and any moneys remaining in the fund shall be refunded to hospitals in proportion to the amounts paid by such hospitals, if and to the extent that any of the following conditions occur:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The federal department of health and human services and a court of competent jurisdiction makes a final determination, with all appeals exhausted, that any element of this chapter, other than RCW
74.60.090
, cannot be validly implemented; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Funds generated by the assessment for payments to medicaid prospective payment hospitals or managed care organizations are determined to be not eligible for federal matching funds in addition to those federal funds that would be received without the assessment, or the federal government replaces medicaid matching funds with a block grant or grants.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This chapter does not take effect or ceases to be imposed, and any moneys remaining in the fund shall be refunded to hospitals in proportion to the amounts paid by such hospitals, if and to the extent that any of the following conditions occur:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Other funding sufficient to maintain aggregate payment levels to hospitals for inpatient and outpatient services covered by medicaid, including fee-for-service and managed care, at least at the rates the state paid for those services on July 1, 2022, as adjusted for current enrollment and utilization is not appropriated or available;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Payments required by this chapter are reduced, except as specifically authorized in this chapter, or payments are not made in substantial compliance with the time frames set forth in this chapter; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_150__subsec_3__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount of assessment funds authorized to be used in lieu of state general fund payments for medicaid hospital services is increased above the amount stated in RCW
74.60.020
or the fund is otherwise used as a substitute for or to supplant other funds.
[
2023 c 430 s 13
;
2017 c 228 s 10
;
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5 s 9
;
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17 s 15
;
2010 1st sp.s. c 30 s 17
.]
NOTES:
Contingent effective date
—
2023 c 430:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2017 c 228:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
