<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.160"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.160"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.160/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.160/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.160/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.160/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_60_160">
        <num>RCW 74.60.160</num>
        <heading>Contracting with health care authority</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature intends to provide the hospitals with an opportunity to contract with the authority each fiscal biennium to protect the hospitals from future legislative action during the biennium that could result in hospitals receiving less from supplemental payments, increased managed care payments, disproportionate share hospital payments, or access payments than the hospitals expected to receive in return for the assessment based on the biennial appropriations and assessment legislation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each odd-numbered year after enactment of the biennial omnibus operating appropriations act, the authority shall extend the existing contract for the period of the fiscal biennium beginning July 1st with a hospital that is required to pay the assessment under this chapter or shall offer to enter into a contract with any hospital subject to this chapter that has not previously been a party to a contract or whose contract has expired. The contract must include the following terms:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authority must agree not to do any of the following:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Increase the assessment from the level set by the authority pursuant to this chapter on the first day of the contract period for reasons other than as allowed under this chapter;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Reduce aggregate payment levels to hospitals for inpatient and outpatient services covered by medicaid, including fee-for-service and managed care, adjusting for changes in enrollment and utilization, from the levels the state paid for those services on the first day of the contract period;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For critical access hospitals only, reduce the levels of disproportionate share hospital payments under RCW
74.60.110
or access payments under RCW
74.60.100
for all critical access hospitals below the levels specified in those sections on the first day of the contract period;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For medicaid prospective payment system, psychiatric, and rehabilitation hospitals only, reduce the levels of supplemental payments under RCW
74.60.120
for all medicaid prospective payment system hospitals below the levels specified in that section on the first day of the contract period unless the supplemental payments are reduced under RCW
74.60.120</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For medicaid prospective payment system, psychiatric, and rehabilitation hospitals only, reduce the increased payments to managed care organizations under RCW
74.60.130
below the levels specified in that section on the first day of the contract period unless the managed care payments are reduced under RCW
74.60.130</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_v__subsec_vi">
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as specified in this chapter, use assessment revenues for any other purpose than to secure federal medicaid matching funds to support payments to hospitals for medicaid services; and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As long as payment levels are maintained as required under this chapter, the hospital must agree not to challenge the authority's reduction of hospital reimbursement rates to July 1, 2009, levels, which results from the elimination of assessment supported rate restorations and increases, under 42 U.S.C. Sec. 1396a(a)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>either through administrative appeals or in court during the period of the contract.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a court finds that the authority has breached an agreement with a hospital under subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section, the authority:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Must immediately refund any assessment payments made subsequent to the breach by that hospital upon receipt; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>May discontinue supplemental payments, increased managed care payments, disproportionate share hospital payments, and access payments made subsequent to the breach for the hospital that are required under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_160__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The remedies provided in this section are not exclusive of any other remedies and rights that may be available to the hospital whether provided in this chapter or otherwise in law, equity, or statute.
[
2023 c 430 s 14
;
2017 c 228 s 11
;
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5 s 10
;
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17 s 17
.]
NOTES:
Contingent effective date
—
2023 c 430:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2017 c 228:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
