<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.090"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.090"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.090/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.090/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.090/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.090/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_60_090">
        <num>RCW 74.60.090</num>
        <heading>Medicaid directed payment program</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In consultation with the Washington state hospital association, the authority shall design and implement a medicaid directed payment program, consistent with 42 C.F.R. Sec. 438.6(c), intended to promote access to high quality inpatient and outpatient care provided by designated public hospitals to medicaid beneficiaries enrolled in managed care organizations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The directed payment program described in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section shall promote access and improve the equitable distribution of care to underserved populations by increasing payments to managed care organizations for the purpose of increasing reimbursement of designated public hospitals for inpatient and outpatient services provided to managed care enrollees, to 95 percent of the centers for medicare and medicaid services allowable limit, plus an estimated amount to support each eligible hospital's participation in the quality incentive program under RCW
74.09.611
, which shall be allocated solely to eligible designated public hospitals pursuant to RCW
74.60.020</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Payments to individual managed care organizations shall be determined by the authority based on each managed care organization's payments made to designated public hospitals for medicaid inpatient and outpatient services. The authority shall make this determination in consultation with the Washington state hospital association.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Managed care organizations shall make directed payments described in this section to designated public hospitals within 21 calendar days of receiving the full amount of funds from the authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The managed care organization payments made pursuant to this section shall be derived from intergovernmental transfers voluntarily made by, and accepted from, designated public hospitals.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_5__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Participation in the intergovernmental transfers used to fund the program described by this section is voluntary on the part of transferring entities for the purposes of all applicable federal laws.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_5__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All funds associated with intergovernmental transfers made and accepted pursuant to this section must be used either to fund additional managed care organization payments under this section to benefit designated public hospitals or, for those designated public hospitals determined to be eligible for payment under RCW
74.09.611
, for deposit into the hospital safety net assessment fund established under RCW
74.60.020
solely for the purpose of providing funding, under RCW
74.60.020</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_5__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Medicaid managed care organizations shall pay on a quarterly basis 100 percent of any payments made pursuant to this section to designated public hospitals, less an allowance for premium taxes the organization is required to pay under Title
48
RCW, for the purpose of promoting access and increasing the quality of care delivered to medicaid enrollees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The intergovernmental transfers associated with the direct payments described in this section shall be collected by the authority within a reasonable time frame in relation to the date on which the state is required to furnish each hospital's nonfederal share of expenditures pursuant to the program described by this section and approved by the centers for medicare and medicaid services or after a determination of eligibility is made, for the program described under RCW
74.09.611
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As a condition of participation under this section, medicaid managed care organizations and designated public hospitals shall:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Agree to comply with any requests for information or similar data requirements imposed by the authority for purposes of obtaining supporting documentation necessary to claim federal funds or to obtain federal approvals; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Agree to participate in and provide requested data associated with payment arrangement quality strategy goals and objectives identified by the approved program.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section shall be implemented only if and to the extent federal financial participation is available and is not otherwise jeopardized, and any necessary federal approvals have been obtained.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>To the extent that the director determines that the payments made pursuant to this section do not comply with federal medicaid requirements, the director retains the discretion to return or not accept all or a portion of an intergovernmental transfer, and may adjust payments pursuant to this section as necessary to comply with federal medicaid requirements.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_090__subsec_10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Conditioned upon required federal approvals, the directed payments under this section shall commence January 1, 2024. If federal approval is obtained after January 1, 2024, the payments shall commence within 30 calendar days following the approval.
[
2023 c 430 s 8
;
2021 c 255 s 3
;
2019 c 318 s 6
;
2017 c 228 s 6
;
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5 s 5
;
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17 s 8
;
2011 1st sp.s. c 35 s 2
;
2010 1st sp.s. c 30 s 10
.]
NOTES:
Contingent effective date
—
2023 c 430:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2019 c 318:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2017 c 228:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17:
See note following RCW
74.60.005
.
Effective date
—
2011 1st sp.s. c 35:
See note following RCW
74.60.020
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
