<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.08.278"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.08.278"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.08.278/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.08.278/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.08.278/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.08.278/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_08_278">
        <num>RCW 74.08.278</num>
        <heading>Central operating fund established</heading>
        <content>
          <p>Print
RCWs
&gt;
Title 74
&gt;
Chapter 74.08
&gt;
Section 74.08.278
74.08.260
&lt;&lt; 
        74.08.278 &gt;&gt;
74.08.280
PDF
RCW
74.08.278
Central operating fund established.
In order to comply with federal statutes and regulations pertaining to federal matching funds and to provide for the prompt payment of initial grants and adjusting payments of grants the secretary is authorized to make provisions for the cash payment of assistance by the secretary or county administrators by the establishment of a central operating fund. The secretary may establish such a fund with the approval of the state auditor from moneys appropriated to the department for the payment of benefits under RCW
74.62.030
in a sum not to exceed one million dollars. Such funds shall be deposited as agreed upon by the secretary and the state auditor in accordance with the laws regulating the deposits of public funds. Such security shall be required of the depository in connection with the fund as the state treasurer may prescribe. Moneys remaining in the fund shall be returned to the general fund at the end of the biennium, or an accounting of proper expenditures from the fund shall be made to the state auditor. All expenditures from such central operating fund shall be reimbursed out of and charged to the proper program appropriated by the use of such forms and vouchers as are approved by the secretary of the department and the state auditor. Expenditures from such fund shall be audited by the director of financial management and the state auditor from time to time and a report shall be made by the state auditor and the secretary as are required by law.
[
2011 1st sp.s. c 36 s 28
;
2010 1st sp.s. c 8 s 25
;
1979 c 141 s 327
;
1959 c 26 s 74.08.278
. Prior:
1953 c 174 s 42
;
1951 c 261 s 1
.]
NOTES:
Findings
—
Intent
—
2011 1st sp.s. c 36:
See RCW
74.62.005
.
Effective date
—
2011 1st sp.s. c 36:
See note following RCW
74.62.005
.
Findings
—
Intent
—
Short title
—
Effective date
—
2010 1st sp.s. c 8:
See notes following RCW
74.04.225
.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
