<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.045"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.045"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.045/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.045/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.045/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.045/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_13A_045">
        <num>RCW 74.13A.045</num>
        <heading>Adoptive parent's financial information</heading>
        <content>
          <p>Print
RCWs
&gt;
Title 74
&gt;
Chapter 74.13A
&gt;
Section 74.13A.045
74.13A.040
&lt;&lt; 
        74.13A.045 &gt;&gt;
74.13A.047
PDF
RCW
74.13A.045
Adoptive parent's financial information.
So long as any adoptive parent is receiving support pursuant to RCW
26.33.320
and *
74.13.100
through
74.13.145
he or she shall, upon request, file with the secretary a copy of his or her federal income tax return. Such return and any information thereon shall be marked by the secretary &quot;confidential&quot;, shall be used by the secretary solely for the purposes of RCW
26.33.320
and *
74.13.100
through
74.13.145
, and shall not be revealed to any other person, institution or agency, public or private, including agencies of the United States government, other than a superior court, judge or commissioner before whom a petition for adoption of a child being supported or to be supported pursuant to RCW
26.33.320
and *
74.13.100
through
74.13.145
is then pending.
In carrying on the review process authorized by RCW
26.33.320
and *
74.13.100
through
74.13.145
the secretary may require the adoptive parent or parents to disclose such additional financial information, not privileged, as may enable him or her to make determinations and adjustments in support to the end that the purposes and policies of this state expressed in *RCW
74.13.100
may be carried out, provided that no adoptive parent or parents shall be obliged, by virtue of this section, to sign any agreement or other writing waiving any constitutional right or privilege nor to admit to his or her home any agent, employee, or official of any department of this state, or of the United States government.
Such information shall be marked &quot;confidential&quot; by the secretary, shall be used by him or her solely for the purposes of RCW
26.33.320
and *
74.13.100
through
74.13.145
, and shall not be revealed to any other person, institution, or agency, public or private, including agencies of the United States government other than a superior court judge or commission before whom a petition for adoption of a child being supported or to be supported pursuant to RCW
26.33.320
and *
74.13.100
through
74.13.145
is then pending.
[
1995 c 270 s 3
;
1985 c 7 s 139
;
1971 ex.s. c 63 s 8
. Formerly RCW
74.13.121
.]
NOTES:
*Reviser's note:
RCW
74.13.100
through
74.13.145
were recodified as RCW
74.13A.005
through
74.13A.080
pursuant to
2009 c 520 s 95
.
Finding
—
1995 c 270:
See note following RCW
74.13A.040
.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
