<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.120"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.120"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.120/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.120/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.120/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.120/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_13A_120">
        <num>RCW 74.13A.120</num>
        <heading>Interstate agreements for adoption of children with special needs—Medical assistance for children residing in this state—Penalty for fraudulent claims</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_13A_120__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A child with special needs who resides in this state and is the subject of an adoption assistance agreement with another state is entitled to receive a medical assistance identification card from this state upon the filing with the department of a certified copy of the adoption assistance agreement obtained from the adoption assistance state. In accordance with regulations of the medical assistance administration, the adoptive parents are required at least annually to show that the agreement is still in force or has been renewed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_13A_120__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The medical assistance administration shall consider the holder of a medical assistance identification under this section as any other holder of a medical assistance identification under the laws of this state and shall process and make payment on claims in the same manner and under the same conditions and procedures as for other recipients of medical assistance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_13A_120__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The medical assistance administration shall provide coverage and benefits for a child who is in another state and is covered by an adoption assistance agreement made by the department for the coverage or benefits, if any, not provided by the residence state. Adoptive parents acting for the child may submit evidence of payment for services or benefit amounts not payable in the residence state for reimbursement. No reimbursement may be made for services or benefit amounts covered under any insurance or other third party medical contract or arrangement held by the child or the adoptive parents. The department shall adopt rules implementing this subsection. The additional coverage and benefit amounts provided under this subsection must be for services to the cost of which there is no federal contribution, or which, if federally aided, are not provided by the residence state. The rules must include procedures to be followed in obtaining prior approval for services if required for the assistance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_13A_120__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The submission of any claim for payment or reimbursement for services or benefits under this section or the making of any statement that the person knows or should know to be false, misleading, or fraudulent is punishable as perjury under chapter
9A.72
RCW.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_13A_120__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section applies only to medical assistance for children under adoption assistance agreements from states that have entered into a compact with this state under which the other state provided medical assistance to children with special needs under adoption assistance agreements made by this state. All other children entitled to medical assistance under an adoption assistance agreement entered into by this state are eligible to receive assistance in accordance with the applicable laws and procedures.
[
1997 c 31 s 7
. Formerly RCW
74.13.158
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
