<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.63.020"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.63.020"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.63.020/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.63.020/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.63.020/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.63.020/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_63_020">
        <num>RCW 82.63.020</num>
        <heading>Application—Annual tax performance report—Reports</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_63_020__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Application for deferral of taxes under this chapter must be made before initiation of construction of, or acquisition of equipment or machinery for the investment project. In the case of an investment project involving multiple qualified buildings, applications must be made for, and before the initiation of construction of, each qualified building. The application must be made to the department in a form and manner prescribed by the department. The application must contain information regarding the location of the investment project, the applicant's average employment in the state for the prior year, estimated or actual new employment related to the project, estimated or actual wages of employees related to the project, estimated or actual costs, time schedules for completion and operation, and other information required by the department. The department must rule on the application within sixty days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_63_020__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each recipient of a deferral of taxes under this chapter must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
. If the economic benefits of the deferral are passed to a lessee as provided in RCW
82.63.010</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_63_020__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A recipient who must repay deferred taxes under RCW
82.63.045
because the department has found that an investment project is used for purposes other than research and development performed within this state in the fields of advanced computing, advanced materials, biotechnology, electronic device technology, and environmental technology is no longer required to file annual tax performance reports under RCW
82.32.534
beginning on the date an investment project is used for nonqualifying purposes.
[
2017 c 135 s 37
;
2010 c 114 s 140
;
2009 c 268 s 3
;
2004 c 2 s 4
;
1994 sp.s. c 5 s 4
.]
NOTES:
Effective date
—
2017 c 135:
See note following RCW
82.32.534
.
Application
—
Finding
—
Intent
—
2010 c 114:
See notes following RCW
82.32.534
.
Policy
—
Application
—
2009 c 268:
See notes following RCW
82.63.090
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
