<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.24.080"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.24.080"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.24.080/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.24.080/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.24.080/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.24.080/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_24_080">
        <num>RCW 82.24.080</num>
        <heading>Legislative intent—Taxable event—Tax liability</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_24_080__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is the intent and purpose of this chapter to levy a tax on all of the articles taxed under this chapter, sold, used, consumed, handled, possessed, or distributed within this state and to collect the tax from the person who first sells, uses, consumes, handles, possesses (either physically or constructively, in accordance with RCW
82.24.020
) or distributes them in the state. It is further the intent and purpose of this chapter that whenever any of the articles taxed under this chapter is given away for advertising or any other purpose, it shall be taxed in the same manner as if it were sold, used, consumed, handled, possessed, or distributed in this state.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_24_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is also the intent and purpose of this chapter that the tax shall be imposed at the time and place of the first taxable event and upon the first taxable person within this state. Any person whose activities would otherwise require payment of the tax imposed by subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_24_080__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section but who is exempt from the tax nevertheless has a precollection obligation for the tax that must be imposed on the first taxable event within this state. A precollection obligation may not be imposed upon a person exempt from the tax who sells, distributes, or transfers possession of cigarettes to another person who, by law, is exempt from the tax imposed by this chapter or upon whom the obligation for collection of the tax may not be imposed. Failure to pay the tax with respect to a taxable event shall not prevent tax liability from arising by reason of a subsequent taxable event.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_24_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the event of an increase in the rate of the tax imposed under this chapter, it is the intent of the legislature that the first person who sells, uses, consumes, handles, possesses, or distributes previously taxed articles after the effective date of the rate increase shall be liable for the additional tax, or its precollection obligation as required by this chapter, represented by the rate increase. The failure to pay the additional tax with respect to the first taxable event after the effective date of a rate increase shall not prevent tax liability for the additional tax from arising from a subsequent taxable event.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_24_080__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is the intent of the legislature that, in the absence of a cigarette tax contract or agreement under chapter
43.06
RCW, applicable taxes imposed by this chapter be collected on cigarettes sold by an Indian tribal organization to any person who is not an enrolled member of the federally recognized Indian tribe within whose jurisdiction the sale takes place consistent with collection of these taxes generally within the state. The legislature finds that applicable collection and enforcement measures under this chapter are reasonably necessary to prevent fraudulent transactions and place a minimal burden on the Indian tribal organization, pursuant to the United States supreme court's decision in
Washington v. Confederated Tribes of the Colville Indian Reservation
, 447 U.S. 134</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
