<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.90.050"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.90.050"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.90.050/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.90.050/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.90.050/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.90.050/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_90_050">
        <num>RCW 82.90.050</num>
        <heading>Requirements for recipients—Meaningful construction</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_90_050__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The recipient of a deferral certificate under RCW
82.90.040
must begin meaningful construction on an eligible investment project within one year of receiving a deferral certificate, unless construction was delayed due to circumstances beyond the recipient's control. Lack of funding is not considered a circumstance beyond the recipient's control.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_90_050__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the recipient does not begin meaningful construction on an eligible investment project within one year of receiving a deferral certificate, the deferral certificate issued under RCW
82.90.040
is invalid and taxes deferred under this chapter are due immediately.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_90_050__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A recipient of a deferral certificate under RCW
82.90.040
must notify the department and update the information originally provided in the application if the solar canopy, at the time of completion, will produce an amount of electricity that is less than 85 percent of the nameplate capacity originally assumed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_90_050__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each recipient of a deferral of taxes under this chapter must file a complete annual tax performance report with the department under RCW
82.32.534
for the year the solar canopy is certified as operationally complete and for the subsequent seven years. If the solar canopy ceases to be connected to the electrical grid, the annual tax performance report is no longer required beginning on the date the solar canopy was disconnected from the electrical grid.
[
2022 c 161 s 5
.]
NOTES:
Tax preference performance statement
—
Automatic tax preference expiration
—
Exception
—
2022 c 161:
See notes following RCW
82.90.040
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
