<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.052"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.052"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.052/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.052/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.052/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.052/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_08_052">
        <num>RCW 82.08.052</num>
        <heading>Remote seller—Nexus</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and this subsection, if the seller, in the current or immediately preceding calendar year, had:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>More than one hundred thousand dollars of cumulative gross receipts from this state;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the limitation in</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the limitation in RCW
82.32.531
, physical presence in this state under RCW
82.04.067
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Cumulative gross receipts counting toward the threshold in (a)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection include a person's gross income of the business from all retail sales made by the seller and sourced to this state under RCW
82.32.730
.
(c)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Transactions counting toward the threshold in (a)</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection include all retail sales transactions made by the seller and sourced to this state under RCW
82.32.730
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>From March 14, 2019, a seller is relieved of the obligation to collect the taxes imposed under this chapter and remit those taxes to the department if that obligation arose solely based on the threshold in</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of the threshold in</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection &quot;transaction&quot; means an agreement to furnish a product or products for consideration, and includes a sale as defined in RCW
82.04.040
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The term &quot;transaction&quot; does not include an agreement if the agreement is canceled or rescinded before any of the products are delivered to the buyer or other recipient designated by the buyer, the seller retains no part of the consideration from the buyer, and the seller did not collect from the buyer any tax imposed or authorized under this title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With regard to agreements requiring multiple payments by the consumer, such as a lease, rental, or installment sale, such agreements count as a single transaction for purposes of this subsection, regardless of the number of payments required under the agreement. However, any modification of such an agreement that provides for additional payments is counted as an additional transaction.
(d)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection include, in addition to the cumulative gross receipts and separate transactions of its own sales, the cumulative gross receipts and separate transactions from sales by all marketplace sellers through the marketplace facilitator's marketplace, including marketplace sellers that are not obligated to collect the taxes under this chapter pursuant to the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a purchase made by one consumer through a marketplace facilitator, where the purchase involves sales by multiple marketplace sellers, the purchase is deemed to be one transaction for the marketplace facilitator and one transaction apiece for each marketplace seller.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Beginning January 1, 2020, a seller with a substantial nexus with this state under RCW
82.04.067
is obligated to collect and remit to the department the taxes imposed under this chapter.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For purposes of this section, the following definitions apply:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Apportionable income&quot; has the same meaning as provided in RCW
82.04.460
.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Gross income of the business&quot; has the same meaning as provided in RCW
82.04.080
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>&quot;Product&quot; has the same meaning as provided in RCW
82.32.023
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The definitions in RCW
82.13.010
apply to this section through June 30, 2019.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A seller whose obligation to collect the taxes imposed under this chapter arises after October 1, 2018, must begin collecting taxes imposed under this chapter as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For a remote seller, on the first day of the first calendar month that is at least thirty days from the date that the remote seller becomes required under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section to collect the taxes imposed under this chapter.
(ii) For a seller that has a physical presence in this state, immediately upon establishing a tax collection obligation under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>affects the ongoing tax collection obligation of any seller that was required, or elected, to collect the taxes imposed under this chapter on or before October 1, 2018.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section is subject to RCW
82.32.762
.
[
2019 c 8 s 106
;
2015 3rd sp.s. c 5 s 202
.]
NOTES:
Effective date
—
2019 c 8 ss 101, 104, 106, 201, 402-405, and 501:
See note following RCW
82.02.250
.
Existing rights and liability
—
Retroactive application
—
2019 c 8:
See notes following RCW
82.02.250
.
Application
—
2017 c 323 s 305:
&quot;Section 305 of this act applies retroactively for the period January 1, 2015, through December 31, 2015.&quot; [
2017 c 323 s 306
.]
Construction
—
2017 c 323:
&quot;Nothing in section 204, chapter 5, Laws of 2015 3rd sp. sess. may be construed as affecting the taxable status in calendar year 2015 of any person with a substantial nexus with this state under RCW
82.04.067
any time on or after January 1, 2015, and before September 1, 2015, with respect to business and occupation taxes on apportionable activities as defined in RCW
82.04.460
.&quot; [
2017 c 323 s 305
.]
Effective dates
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 5:
&quot;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Except as provided otherwise in this section, this act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect August 1, 2015.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Part II of this act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect September 1, 2015.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 5 s 501
.]
Finding
—
Intent
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 5:
&quot;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The commerce clause of the United States Constitution as currently interpreted by the United States supreme court prohibits states from imposing sales or use tax collection obligations on out-of-state businesses unless the business has a substantial nexus with the taxing state.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature recognizes that under the United States supreme court's decision in
Quill Corp. v. North Dakota
, 504 U.S. 298</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature further recognizes that the requisite physical presence can be established directly through a taxpayer's own activities in the taxing state, or indirectly, through independent contractors, agents, or other representatives who act on behalf of the taxpayer in the taxing state.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>However, the legislature finds that because the United States supreme court has not clearly defined the circumstances under which a physical presence is sufficient to establish a substantial nexus for tax purposes, frequent conflicts have arisen throughout the country among state taxing authorities, taxpayers, tax practitioners, and courts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_052__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Therefore, the legislature intends to provide more clarity for out-of-state sellers that compensate Washington residents for referring customers to the out-of-state seller by providing clear statutory guidelines for determining when these out-of-state sellers are required to collect Washington's retail sales tax.&quot; [
2015 3rd sp.s. c 5 s 201
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
