<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.855"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.855"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.855/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.855/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.855/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.855/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_08_855">
        <num>RCW 82.08.855</num>
        <heading>Exemptions—Replacement parts for qualifying farm machinery and equipment</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The tax levied by RCW
82.08.020
does not apply to the sale to an eligible farmer of:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Replacement parts for qualifying farm machinery and equipment;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Labor and services rendered in respect to the installing of replacement parts; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Labor and services rendered in respect to the repairing of qualifying farm machinery and equipment, provided that during the course of repairing no tangible personal property is installed, incorporated, or placed in, or becomes an ingredient or component of, the qualifying farm machinery and equipment other than replacement parts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in this chapter, if a single transaction involves services that are not exempt under this section and services that would be exempt under this section if provided separately, the exemptions provided in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section apply if:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The seller makes a separately itemized charge for labor and services described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section; and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_c__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the separately itemized charge does not exceed the seller's usual and customary charge for such services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the requirements in (a)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>are met, the exemption provided in subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section applies to the separately itemized charge for labor and services described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A purchaser claiming an exemption under this section must keep records necessary for the department to verify eligibility under this section. Sellers making tax-exempt sales under this section must obtain an exemption certificate from the purchaser in a form and manner prescribed by the department. In lieu of an exemption certificate, a seller may capture the relevant data elements as allowed under the streamlined sales and use tax agreement. The seller must retain a copy of the certificate or the data elements for the seller's files.
(b)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For a person who is an eligible farmer as defined in subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this section, the exemption is conditioned upon:
(A) The eligible farmer having gross sales or a harvested value of agricultural products grown, raised, or produced by that person or gross sales of bee pollination services of at least ten thousand dollars in the first full tax year in which the person engages in business as a farmer; or
(B) The eligible farmer, during the first full tax year in which that person engages in business as a farmer, growing, raising, or producing agricultural products or bee pollination services having an estimated value at any time during that year of at least ten thousand dollars, if the person will not sell or harvest an agricultural product or bee pollination service during the first full tax year in which the person engages in business as a farmer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person fails to meet the condition provided in</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>(b)(ii) if full payment is received by the due date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The definitions in this subsection apply throughout this section unless the context clearly requires otherwise.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Agricultural products&quot; has the meaning provided in RCW
82.04.213
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Eligible farmer&quot; means:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A farmer as defined in RCW
82.04.213
whose gross sales or harvested value of agricultural products grown, raised, or produced by that person or gross sales of bee pollination services was at least ten thousand dollars for the immediately preceding tax year;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A farmer as defined in RCW
82.04.213
whose agricultural products had an estimated value of at least ten thousand dollars for the immediately preceding tax year, if the person did not sell or harvest an agricultural product or bee pollination service during that year;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A farmer as defined in RCW
82.04.213
who has merely changed identity or the form of ownership of an entity that was an eligible farmer, where there was no change in beneficial ownership, and the combined gross sales, harvested value, or estimated value of agricultural products or bee pollination services by both entities met the requirements of</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection for the immediately preceding tax year;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A farmer as defined in RCW
82.04.213
who does not meet the definition of &quot;eligible farmer&quot; in</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of this subsection, and who did not engage in farming for the entire immediately preceding tax year, because the farmer is either new to farming or newly returned to farming; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Anyone who otherwise meets the definition of &quot;eligible farmer&quot; in this subsection except that they are not a &quot;person&quot; as defined in RCW
82.04.030
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Farm vehicle&quot; has the same meaning as in RCW
46.04.181
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Harvested value&quot; means the number of units of the agricultural product that were grown, raised, or produced, multiplied by the average sales price of the agricultural product. For purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Qualifying farm machinery and equipment&quot; means machinery and equipment used primarily by an eligible farmer for growing, raising, or producing agricultural products, providing bee pollination services, or both. &quot;Qualifying farm machinery and equipment&quot; does not include:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Vehicles as defined in RCW
46.04.670
, other than farm tractors as defined in RCW
46.04.180
, farm vehicles, and other farm implements. For purposes of this subsection</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Aircraft;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Hand tools and hand-powered tools; and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property with a useful life of less than one year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Replacement parts&quot; means those parts that replace an existing part, or which are essential to maintain the working condition, of a piece of qualifying farm machinery or equipment.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Paint, fuel, oil, hydraulic fluids, antifreeze, and similar items are not replacement parts except when installed, incorporated, or placed in qualifying farm machinery and equipment during the course of installing replacement parts as defined in</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection or making repairs as described in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_08_855__subsec_4__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Tax year&quot; means the period for which a person files its federal income tax return, irrespective of whether the period represents a calendar year, fiscal year, or some other consecutive twelve-month period. If a person is not required to file a federal income tax return, &quot;tax year&quot; means a calendar year.
[
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 s 1106
;
2014 c 97 s 601
;
2007 c 332 s 1
;
2006 c 172 s 1
.]
NOTES:
Effective dates
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6:
See note following RCW
82.04.4266
.
Tax preference performance statement
—
Tax preference intended to be permanent
—
2015 3rd sp.s. c 6 ss 1102-1106:
See notes following RCW
82.04.330
.
Effective date
—
2006 c 172:
&quot;This act takes effect July 1, 2006.&quot; [
2006 c 172 s 3
.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
