<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.9994"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.9994"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.9994/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.9994/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.9994/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.9994/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_08_9994">
        <num>RCW 82.08.9994</num>
        <heading>Exemptions—Bottled water—Prescription use</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_9994__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the conditions in this section, the tax levied by RCW
82.08.020
does not apply to sales of bottled water dispensed or to be dispensed to patients pursuant to a prescription for use in the cure, mitigation, treatment, or prevention of disease or medical condition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_9994__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For purposes of this section, &quot;prescription&quot; means an order, formula, or recipe issued in any form of oral, written, electronic, or other means of transmission by a duly licensed practitioner authorized by the laws of this state to prescribe.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_9994__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Except for sales of bottled water delivered to the buyer in a reusable container that is not sold with the water, sellers must collect tax on sales subject to this exemption. Any buyer that has paid at least twenty-five dollars in state and local sales taxes on purchases of bottled water subject to this exemption may apply for a refund of the taxes directly from the department in a form and manner prescribed by the department. The department must deny any refund application if the amount of the refund requested is less than twenty-five dollars. No refund may be made for taxes paid more than four years after the end of the calendar year in which the tax was paid to the seller.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_9994__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With respect to sales of bottled water delivered to the buyer in a reusable container that is not sold with the water, buyers claiming the exemption provided in this section must provide the seller with an exemption certificate in a form and manner prescribed by the department. The seller must retain a copy of the certificate for the seller's files.
[
2017 3rd sp.s. c 28 s 103
.]
NOTES:
Reviser's note:
The tax preference enacted in section 103, chapter 28, Laws of 2017 3rd sp. sess. expires January 1, 2028, pursuant to the automatic expiration date in RCW
82.32.805</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
