<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.0202"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.0202"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.0202/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.0202/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.0202/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.0202/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_08_0202">
        <num>RCW 82.08.0202</num>
        <heading>Retail sales of linen and uniform supply services</heading>
        <content>
          <p>Print
RCWs
&gt;
Title 82
&gt;
Chapter 82.08
&gt;
Section 82.08.0202
82.08.0201
&lt;&lt; 
        82.08.0202 &gt;&gt;
82.08.0203
PDF
RCW
82.08.0202
Retail sales of linen and uniform supply services.
For purposes of this chapter, a retail sale of linen and uniform supply services is deemed to occur at the place of delivery to the customer. &quot;Linen and uniform supply services&quot; means the activity of providing customers with a supply of clean linen, towels, uniforms, gowns, protective apparel, clean room apparel, mats, rugs, and similar items, whether ownership of the item is in the person operating the linen and uniform supply service or in the customer. The term includes supply services operating their own cleaning establishments as well as those contracting with other laundry or dry cleaning businesses.
[
2001 c 186 s 2
.]
NOTES:
Finding
—
Purpose
—
2001 c 186:
&quot;The legislature finds that because of the mixed retailing nature of linen and uniform supply services, they have been incorrectly sited for tax purposes. As a result, some companies that perform some activities related to this activity outside the state of Washington have not been required to collect retail sales taxes upon linen and uniform supply services provided to Washington customers. The activity has aspects of both the rental of tangible personal property and retail services related to tangible personal property. This error in tax treatment provides an incentive for businesses to locate some of their functions out of state. In-state businesses cannot compete if their out-of-state competitors are not required to collect sales tax for services provided to the same customers.
The purpose of this act is to clarify the taxable situs and nature of linen and uniform supply services.&quot; [
2001 c 186 s 1
.]
Effective date
—
2001 c 186:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 2001.&quot; [
2001 c 186 s 4
.]</p>
        </content>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
