<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.02566"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.02566"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.02566/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.02566/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.02566/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.08.02566/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_08_02566">
        <num>RCW 82.08.02566</num>
        <heading>Exemptions—Sales of tangible personal property incorporated in prototype for parts, auxiliary equipment, and aircraft modification—Limitations on yearly exemption</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_02566__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The tax levied by RCW
82.08.020
shall not apply to sales of tangible personal property incorporated into a prototype for aircraft parts, auxiliary equipment, or modifications; or to sales of tangible personal property that at one time is incorporated into the prototype but is later destroyed in the testing or development of the prototype.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_02566__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This exemption does not apply to sales to any person whose total taxable amount during the immediately preceding calendar year exceeds twenty million dollars. For purposes of this section, &quot;total taxable amount&quot; means gross income of the business and value of products manufactured, less any amounts for which a credit is allowed under RCW
82.04.440
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_02566__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>State and local taxes for which an exemption is received under this section and RCW
82.12.02566
shall not exceed one hundred thousand dollars for any person during any calendar year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_08_02566__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Sellers shall collect tax on sales subject to this exemption. The buyer shall apply for a refund directly from the department.
[
2003 c 168 s 208
;
1997 c 302 s 1
;
1996 c 247 s 4
.]
NOTES:
Effective dates
—
Part headings not law
—
2003 c 168:
See notes following RCW
82.08.010
.
Effective date
—
1997 c 302:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 1997.&quot; [
1997 c 302 s 3
.]
Findings
—
Intent
—
1996 c 247:
&quot;The legislature finds that the health, safety, and welfare of the people of the state of Washington are heavily dependent upon the continued encouragement, development, and expansion of opportunities for family wage employment in the state's manufacturing industries.
The legislature also finds that sales and use tax exemptions for manufacturing machinery and equipment enacted by the 1995 legislature have improved Washington's ability to compete with other states for manufacturing investment, but that additional incentives for manufacturers need to be adopted to solidify and enhance the state's competitive position.
The legislature intends to accomplish this by extending the current manufacturing machinery and equipment exemptions to include machinery and equipment used for research and development with potential manufacturing applications.&quot; [
1996 c 247 s 1
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
