<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.34.220"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.34.220"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.34.220/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.34.220/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.34.220/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.34.220/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_34_220">
        <num>RCW 74.34.220</num>
        <heading>Financial exploitation of vulnerable adults—Training—Reporting</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_34_220__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A financial institution shall provide training concerning the financial exploitation of vulnerable adults to the employees specified in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_34_220__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section within one year of June 10, 2010, and shall thereafter provide such training to the new employees specified in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_34_220__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section within the first three months of their employment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_34_220__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A financial institution that is a broker-dealer or investment adviser as defined in RCW
21.20.005
shall provide training concerning the financial exploitation of vulnerable adults to employees who are required to be registered in the state of Washington as salespersons or investment adviser representatives under RCW
21.20.040
and who have contact with customers and access to account information on a regular basis and as part of their job. All other financial institutions shall provide training concerning the financial exploitation of vulnerable adults to employees who have contact with customers and access to account information on a regular basis and as part of their job.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_34_220__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The training must include recognition of indicators of financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult, the manner in which employees may report suspected financial exploitation to the department and law enforcement as permissive reporters, and steps employees may take to prevent suspected financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult as authorized by law or agreements between the financial institution and customers of the financial institution. The office of the attorney general and the department shall develop a standardized training that financial institutions may offer, or the financial institution may develop its own training.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_34_220__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A financial institution may provide access to or copies of records that are relevant to suspected financial exploitation or attempted financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult to the department, law enforcement, or the prosecuting attorney's office, either as part of a referral to the department, law enforcement, or the prosecuting attorney's office, or upon request of the department, law enforcement, or the prosecuting attorney's office pursuant to an investigation. The records may include historical records as well as records relating to the most recent transaction or transactions that may comprise financial exploitation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_34_220__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A financial institution or employee of a financial institution participating in good faith in making a report or providing documentation or access to information to the department, law enforcement, or the prosecuting attorney's office under this chapter shall be immune from criminal, civil, or administrative liability.
[
2010 c 133 s 5
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
