<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.540"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.540"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.540/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.540/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.540/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.540/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_14_540">
        <num>RCW 82.14.540</num>
        <heading>Affordable and supportive housing—Sales and use tax</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The definitions in this subsection apply throughout this section unless the context clearly requires otherwise.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Nonparticipating city&quot; is a city that does not impose a sales and use tax in accordance with the terms of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Nonparticipating county&quot; is a county that does not impose a sales and use tax in accordance with the terms of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Participating city&quot; is a city that imposes a sales and use tax in accordance with the terms of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Participating county&quot; is a county that imposes a sales and use tax in accordance with the terms of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Qualifying local tax&quot; means the following tax sources, if the tax source is instated no later than twelve months after July 28, 2019:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The affordable housing levy authorized under RCW
84.52.105
;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sales and use tax for housing and related services authorized under RCW
82.14.530
, provided the city has imposed the tax at a minimum or of at least half of the authorized rate;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sales tax for chemical dependency and mental health treatment services or therapeutic courts authorized under RCW
82.14.460
imposed by a city; and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The levy authorized under RCW
84.55.050
, if used solely for affordable housing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A county or city legislative authority may authorize, fix, and impose a sales and use tax in accordance with the terms of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax under this section is assessed on the selling price in the case of a sales tax, or value of the article used, in the case of a use tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The rate of the tax under this section for an individual participating city and an individual participating county may not exceed:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Beginning on July 28, 2019, until twelve months after July 28, 2019:
(A) 0.0073 percent for a:
(I) Participating city, unless the participating city levies a qualifying local tax; and
(II) Participating county, within the limits of nonparticipating cities within the county and within participating cities that do not currently levy a qualifying tax;
(B) 0.0146 percent for a:
(I) Participating city that currently levies a qualifying local tax;
(II) Participating city if the county in which it is located declares they will not levy the sales and use tax authorized under this section or does not adopt a resolution in accordance with this section; and
(III) Participating county within the unincorporated areas of the county and any city that declares they will not levy the sales and use tax authorized under this section or does not adopt a resolution in accordance with this section;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning twelve months after July 28, 2019:
(A) 0.0073 percent for a:
(I) Participating city that is located within a participating county if the participating city is not levying a qualifying local tax; and
(II) Participating county, within the limits of a participating city if the participating city is not levying a qualifying local tax;
(B) 0.0146 percent within the limits of a:
(I) Participating city that is levying a qualifying local tax; and
(II) Participating county within the unincorporated area of the county and within the limits of any nonparticipating city that is located within the county.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A county may not levy the tax authorized under this section within the limits of a participating city that levies a qualifying local tax.
(e)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In order for a county or city legislative authority to impose the tax under this section, the authority must adopt:
(A) A resolution of intent to adopt legislation to authorize the maximum capacity of the tax in this section within six months of July 28, 2019; and
(B) Legislation to authorize the maximum capacity of the tax in this section within one year of July 28, 2019.</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Adoption of the resolution of intent and legislation requires simple majority approval of the enacting legislative authority.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a county or city has not adopted a resolution of intent in accordance with the terms of this section, the county or city may not authorize, fix, and impose the tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The tax imposed under this section must be deducted from the amount of tax otherwise required to be collected or paid to the department of revenue under chapter
82.08
or
82.12
RCW. The department must perform the collection of such taxes on behalf of the county or city at no cost to the county or city.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>By December 31, 2019, or within thirty days of a county or city authorizing the tax under this section, whichever is later, the department must calculate the maximum amount of tax distributions for each county and city authorizing the tax under this section as follows:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The maximum amount for a participating county equals the taxable retail sales within the county in state fiscal year 2019 multiplied by the tax rate imposed under this section. If a county imposes a tax authorized under this section after a city located in that county has imposed the tax, the taxable retail sales within the city in state fiscal year 2019 must be subtracted from the taxable retail sales within the county for the calculation of the maximum amount; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The maximum amount for a city equals the taxable retail sales within the city in state fiscal year 2019 multiplied by the tax rate imposed under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The tax must cease to be distributed to a county or city for the remainder of any fiscal year in which the amount of tax exceeds the maximum amount in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section. The department must remit any annual tax revenues above the maximum to the state treasurer for deposit in the general fund. Distributions to a county or city meeting the maximum amount must resume at the beginning of the next fiscal year.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The moneys collected or bonds issued under this section may only be used for the following purposes:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Acquiring, rehabilitating, or constructing affordable housing, which may include new units of affordable housing within an existing structure or facilities providing supportive housing services under RCW
71.24.385
;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Funding the operations and maintenance costs of new units of affordable or supportive housing; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For providing rental assistance to tenants.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Administrative costs of the county or city associated with administering this section may not exceed 10 percent of the annual tax distributed to the jurisdiction under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The housing and services provided pursuant to subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section may only be provided to persons whose income is at or below 60 percent of the median income of the county or city imposing the tax, or at or below 80 percent of the median income of the county or city imposing the tax if it is supporting the development of affordable housing intended for owner occupancy, as defined in RCW
84.14.010
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In determining the use of funds under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, a county or city must consider the income of the individuals and families to be served, the leveraging of the resources made available under this section, and the housing needs within the jurisdiction of the taxing authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>To carry out the purposes of this section including, but not limited to, financing loans or grants to nonprofit organizations or public housing authorities, the legislative authority of the county or city imposing the tax has the authority to issue general obligation or revenue bonds within the limitations now or hereafter prescribed by the laws of this state, and may use, and is authorized to pledge, the moneys collected under this section for repayment of such bonds.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A county or city may enter into an interlocal agreement with one or more counties, cities, or public housing authorities in accordance with chapter
39.34
RCW. The agreement may include, but is not limited to, pooling the tax receipts received under this section, pledging those taxes to bonds issued by one or more parties to the agreement, and allocating the proceeds of the taxes levied or the bonds issued in accordance with such interlocal agreement and this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Counties and cities imposing the tax under this section must report annually to the department of commerce on the collection and use of the revenue. The department of commerce must adopt rules prescribing content of such reports. By December 1, 2019, and annually thereafter, and in compliance with RCW
43.01.036
, the department of commerce must submit a report annually to the appropriate legislative committees with regard to such uses.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_540__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The tax imposed by a county or city under this section expires twenty years after the date on which the tax is first imposed.
[
2024 c 136 s 1
;
2023 c 101 s 2
;
2019 c 338 s 1
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
