<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.18.127"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.18.127"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.18.127/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.18.127/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.18.127/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.18.127/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_18_127">
        <num>RCW 74.18.127</num>
        <heading>Confidentiality of personal information, records—Rules</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Personal information and records obtained and retained by the department concerning applicants and eligible individuals are confidential, are not subject to public disclosure, and may be released only in accordance with law or with this provision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department shall adopt rules and develop contract language to safeguard the confidentiality of all personal information, including photographs and lists of names. Rules and contract language shall ensure that:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Specific safeguards are established to protect all current and future stored personal information;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Specific safeguards and procedures are established for the release of personal health information in accordance with the health insurance portability and accountability act of 1996, 45 C.F.R. 160 through 45 C.F.R. 164;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All applicants and eligible individuals and, as appropriate, those individuals' representatives, service providers, cooperating agencies, and interested persons are informed upon initial intake of the confidentiality of personal information and the conditions for accessing and releasing this information;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All applicants or their representatives are informed about the department's need to collect personal information and the policies governing its use, including:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Identification of the authority under which information is collected;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>explanation of the principal purposes for which the department intends to use or release the information;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>explanation of whether providing requested information to the department is mandatory or voluntary and the effects of not providing requested information;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_i__subsec_iv">
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <content>
                <p>identification of those situations in which the department requires or does not require informed written consent of the individual before information may be released; and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>identification of other agencies to which information is routinely released; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_18_127__subsec_2__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An explanation of department policies and procedures affecting personal information will be provided at intake or on request to each individual in that individual's native language and in an appropriate format including but not limited to braille, audio recording, electronic media, or large print.
[
2003 c 409 s 12
.]
NOTES:
Findings
—
2003 c 409:
See note following RCW
74.18.010
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
