<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.38.230"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.38.230"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.38.230/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.38.230/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.38.230/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.38.230/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_38_230">
        <num>RCW 82.38.230</num>
        <heading>Delinquency—Seizure and sale of property—Notice—Distribution of excess</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_38_230__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a person is delinquent in the payment of any obligation, and the delinquency continues after notice and demand for payment the department must collect the amount due. The department must seize any property subject to the lien of excise tax, penalty, and interest and sell it at public auction. Notice of sale and the time and place must be given to the person and to all persons appearing with an interest in the property. The notice must be in writing at least ten days before the date of sale. Notice must be published for at least ten days before the date of sale in a newspaper of general circulation published in the county the property will be sold. If there is no newspaper of general circulation in the county, the notice must be posted in three public places in the county for a period of ten days. The notice must contain a description of the property together with a statement of the amount due, the name of the person, and a statement that unless the amount is paid on or before the time in the notice the property will be sold.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_38_230__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department must sell the property and deliver to the purchaser a bill of sale or deed. If the moneys received exceed the amount due from the person, the excess must be returned to the person and a receipt obtained. If any person having an interest in or lien upon the property has filed notice with the department prior to the sale, the department must withhold payment of any excess to the person pending determination of the rights of the respective parties by a court of competent jurisdiction. If the receipt of the person is not available, the department must deposit the excess with the state treasurer as trustee for the person or their heirs, successors, or assigns. Prior to making any seizure of property, the department may first serve upon the person's bondsperson a notice of delinquency and, demand for payment of the amount due.
[
2013 c 225 s 123
;
2007 c 218 s 78
;
1998 c 176 s 77
;
1979 c 40 s 17
;
1971 ex.s. c 175 s 24
.]
NOTES:
Effective date
—
2013 c 225:
See note following RCW
82.38.010
.
Intent
—
Finding
—
2007 c 218:
See note following RCW
41.08.020
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
