<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.860"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.860"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.860/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.860/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.860/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.860/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_09_860">
        <num>RCW 74.09.860</num>
        <heading>Request for proposals—Foster children—Integrated managed health and behavioral health care—Continuation of health care benefits following reunification</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_860__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority shall issue a request for proposals to provide integrated managed health and behavioral health care for foster children receiving care through the medical assistance program. Behavioral health services provided under chapters
71.24
and
71.34
RCW must be integrated into the managed care organization for foster children beginning January 1, 2019. The request for proposals must address the program elements described in section 110, chapter 225, Laws of 2014, including development of a service delivery system, benefit design, reimbursement mechanisms, incorporation or coordination of services currently provided by the regional support networks, and standards for contracting with health organizations. The request for proposals must be issued and completed in time for services under the integrated managed care plan to begin on October 1, 2016.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_860__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The parent or guardian of a child who is no longer a dependent child pursuant to chapter
13.34
RCW may choose to continue in the transitional foster care eligibility category for up to twelve months following reunification with the child's parents or guardian if the child:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_860__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Is under eighteen years of age;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_860__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Was in foster care under the legal responsibility of the department of social and health services, the department of children, youth, and families, or a federally recognized Indian tribe located within the state; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_860__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Meets income and other eligibility standards for medical assistance coverage.
[
2023 c 51 s 52
;
2018 c 27 s 1
;
2015 c 283 s 1
.]
NOTES:
Effective date
—
2018 c 27:
&quot;This act takes effect July 1, 2018.&quot; [
2018 c 27 s 2
.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
