<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.800"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.800"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.800/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.800/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.800/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.800/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_09_800">
        <num>RCW 74.09.800</num>
        <heading>Maternity care access program established</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Provide maternity care services to low-income pregnant women and health care services to children in poverty to the maximum extent allowable under the medical assistance program, Title XIX of the federal social security act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Provide maternity care services to low-income women who are not eligible to receive such services under the medical assistance program, Title XIX of the federal social security act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Have the following procedures in place to improve access to maternity care services and eligibility determinations for pregnant women applying for maternity care services under the medical assistance program, Title XIX of the federal social security act:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Use of a shortened and simplified application form;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Outstationing authority staff to make eligibility determinations;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_3__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Establishing local plans at the county and regional level, coordinated by the authority; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_3__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Conducting an interview for the purpose of determining medical assistance eligibility within five working days of the date of an application by a pregnant woman and making an eligibility determination within fifteen working days of the date of application by a pregnant woman;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Establish a maternity care case management system that shall assist at-risk eligible persons with obtaining medical assistance benefits and receiving maternity care services, including transportation and child care services;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Within available resources, establish appropriate reimbursement levels for maternity care providers;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Implement a broad-based public education program that stresses the importance of obtaining maternity care early during pregnancy;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Refer persons eligible for maternity care services under the program established by this section to persons, agencies, or organizations with maternity care service practices that primarily emphasize healthy birth outcomes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Provide family planning services including information about the synthetic progestin capsule implant form of contraception, for twelve months immediately following a pregnancy to women who were eligible for medical assistance under the maternity care access program during that pregnancy or who were eligible only for emergency labor and delivery services during that pregnancy; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Within available resources, provide family planning services to women who meet the financial eligibility requirements for services under subsections</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_800__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section.
[
2011 1st sp.s. c 15 s 50
;
1993 c 407 s 10
;
1989 1st ex.s. c 10 s 5
.]
NOTES:
Effective date
—
Findings
—
Intent
—
Report
—
Agency transfer
—
References to head of health care authority
—
Draft legislation
—
2011 1st sp.s. c 15:
See notes following RCW
74.09.010
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
