<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.5229"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.5229"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.5229/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.5229/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.5229/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.5229/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_09_5229">
        <num>RCW 74.09.5229</num>
        <heading>Primary care health homes—Chronic care management—Findings—Intent</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_5229__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Health care costs are growing rapidly, exceeding the consumer price index year after year. Consequently, state health programs are capturing a growing share of the state budget, even as state revenues have declined. Sustaining these critical health programs will require actions to effectively contain health care cost increases in the future; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_5229__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The primary care health home model has been demonstrated to successfully constrain costs, while improving quality of care. Chronic care management, occurring within a primary care health home, has been shown to be especially effective at reducing costs and improving quality. However, broad adoption of these models has been impeded by a fee-for-service system that reimburses volume of services and does not adequately support important primary care health home services, such as case management and patient outreach. Furthermore, successful implementation will require a broad adoption effort by private and public payers, in coordination with providers.
Therefore the legislature intends to promote the adoption of primary care health homes for children and adults and, within them, advance the practice of chronic care management to improve health outcomes and reduce unnecessary costs. To facilitate the best coordination and patient care, primary care health homes are encouraged to collaborate with other providers currently outside the medical insurance model. Successful chronic care management for persons receiving long-term care services in addition to medical care will require close coordination between primary care providers, long-term care workers, and other long-term care service providers, including area agencies on aging. Primary care providers also should consider oral health coordination through collaboration with dental providers and, when possible, delivery of oral health prevention services. The legislature also intends that the methods and approach of the primary care health home become part of basic primary care medical education.
[
2011 c 316 s 1
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
