<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.110"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.110"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.110/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.110/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.110/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.110/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_32_110">
        <num>RCW 82.32.110</num>
        <heading>Examination of books or records—Subpoenas—Contempt of court</heading>
        <content>
          <p>Print
RCWs
&gt;
Title 82
&gt;
Chapter 82.32
&gt;
Section 82.32.110
82.32.105
&lt;&lt; 
        82.32.110 &gt;&gt;
82.32.117
PDF
RCW
82.32.110
Examination of books or records
—
Subpoenas
—
Contempt of court.
The department of revenue or its duly authorized agent may examine any books, papers, records, or other data, or stock of merchandise bearing upon the amount of any tax payable or upon the correctness of any return, or for the purpose of making a return where none has been made, or in order to ascertain whether a return should be made; and may require the attendance of any person at a time and place fixed in a summons served by any sheriff in the same manner as a subpoena is served in a civil case, or served in like manner by an agent of the department of revenue.
The persons summoned may be required to testify and produce any books, papers, records, or data required by the department with respect to any tax, or the liability of any person therefor.
The director of the department of revenue, or any duly authorized agent thereof, shall have power to administer an oath to the person required to testify; and any person giving false testimony after the administration of such oath shall be guilty of perjury in the first degree.
If any person summoned as a witness before the department, or its authorized agent, fails or refuses to obey the summons, or refuses to testify or answer any material questions, or to produce any book, record, paper, or data when required to do so, the person is subject to proceedings for contempt, and the department shall thereupon institute contempt of court proceedings in the superior court of Thurston county or of the county in which such person resides.
[
1989 c 373 s 27
;
1975 1st ex.s. c 278 s 79
;
1961 c 15 s 82.32.110
. Prior:
1935 c 180 s 194
; RRS s 8370-194.]
NOTES:
Construction
—
Severability
—
1975 1st ex.s. c 278:
See notes following RCW
11.08.160
.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
