<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.087"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.087"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.087/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.087/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.087/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.32.087/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_32_087">
        <num>RCW 82.32.087</num>
        <heading>Direct pay permits</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The director may grant a direct pay permit to a taxpayer who demonstrates, to the satisfaction of the director, that the taxpayer meets the requirements of this section. The direct pay permit allows the taxpayer to accrue and remit directly to the department use tax on the acquisition of tangible personal property or sales tax on the sale of or charges made for labor and/or services, in accordance with all of the applicable provisions of this title. Any taxpayer that uses a direct pay permit must remit state and local sales or use tax directly to the department. The agreement by the purchaser to remit tax directly to the department, rather than pay sales or use tax to the seller, relieves the seller of the obligation to collect sales or use tax and requires the buyer to pay use tax on the tangible personal property and sales tax on the sale of or charges made for labor and/or services.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxpayer may apply for a permit under this section if:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_1__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The taxpayer's cumulative tax liability is reasonably expected to be two hundred forty thousand dollars or more in the current calendar year; or</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_1__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the taxpayer makes purchases subject to the taxes imposed under chapter
82.08
or
82.12
RCW in excess of ten million dollars per calendar year. For the purposes of this section, &quot;tax liability&quot; means the amount required to be remitted to the department for taxes administered under this chapter, except for the taxes imposed or authorized by chapters
82.14A
, 82.14B, 82.24, 82.27, 82.29A, and
84.33
RCW.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Application for a permit must be made in writing to the director in a form and manner prescribed by the department. A taxpayer who transacts business in two or more locations may submit one application to cover the multiple locations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The director must review a direct pay permit application in a timely manner and must notify the applicant, in writing, of the approval or denial of the application. The department must approve or deny an application based on the applicant's ability to comply with local government use tax coding capabilities and responsibilities; requirements for vendor notification; recordkeeping obligations; electronic data capabilities; and tax reporting procedures. Additionally, an application may be denied if the director determines that denial would be in the best interest of collecting taxes due under this title. The department must provide a direct pay permit to an approved applicant with the notice of approval. The direct pay permit must clearly state that the holder is solely responsible for the accrual and payment of the tax imposed under chapters
82.08
and
82.12
RCW and that the seller is relieved of liability to collect tax imposed under chapters
82.08
and
82.12
RCW on all sales to the direct pay permit holder. The taxpayer may petition the director for reconsideration of a denial.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A taxpayer who uses a direct pay permit must continue to maintain records that are necessary to a determination of the tax liability in accordance with this title. A direct pay permit is not transferable and the use of a direct pay permit may not be assigned to a third party.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Taxes for which the direct pay permit is used are due and payable on the tax return for the reporting period in which the taxpayer</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>receives the tangible personal property purchased or in which the labor and/or services are performed or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>receives an invoice for such property or such labor and/or services, whichever period is earlier.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The holder of a direct pay permit must furnish a copy of the direct pay permit to each vendor with whom the taxpayer has opted to use a direct pay permit. Sellers who make sales upon which the sales or use tax is not collected by reason of the provisions of this section, in addition to existing requirements under this title, must maintain a copy of the direct pay permit and any such records or information as the department may specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A direct pay permit is subject to revocation by the director at any time the department determines that the taxpayer has violated any provision of this section or that revocation would be in the best interests of collecting the taxes due under this title. The notice of revocation must be in writing and is effective either as of the end of the taxpayer's next normal reporting period or a date deemed appropriate by the director and identified in the revocation notice. The taxpayer may petition the director for reconsideration of a revocation and reinstatement of the permit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any taxpayer who chooses to no longer use a direct pay permit or whose permit is revoked by the department, must return the permit to the department and immediately make a good faith effort to notify all vendors to whom the permit was given, advising them that the permit is no longer valid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Except as provided in this subsection, the direct pay permit may be used for any purchase of tangible personal property and any retail sale under RCW
82.04.050
. The direct pay permit may not be used for:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Purchases of meals or beverages;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Purchases of motor vehicles, trailers, boats, airplanes, and other property subject to requirements for title transactions by the department of licensing;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_7__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Purchases for which a reseller permit or other documentation authorized under RCW
82.04.470
may be used;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_7__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Purchases that meet the definitions of *RCW
82.04.050</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_2__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and (f),</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>through (c), (e), (f), and (g),</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_3__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Other activities subject to tax under chapter
82.08
or
82.12
RCW that the department by rule designates, consistent with the purposes of this section, as activities for which a direct pay permit is not appropriate and may not be used.
[
2015 c 169 s 11
;
2010 c 112 s 10
. Prior:
2009 c 563 s 210
;
2009 c 176 s 5
;
2001 c 188 s 2
.]
NOTES:
*
Reviser's note:
RCW
82.04.050
was amended by 2025 c 422 s 101, changing subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_32_087__subsec_3__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
