<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.515"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.515"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.515/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.515/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.515/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.09.515/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_09_515">
        <num>RCW 74.09.515</num>
        <heading>Medical assistance—Coverage for youth released from confinement</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_515__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority shall adopt rules and policies providing that when youth who were enrolled in a medical assistance program immediately prior to confinement are released from confinement, their medical assistance coverage will be fully reinstated on the day of their release, subject to any expedited review of their continued eligibility for medical assistance coverage that is required under federal or state law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_515__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority, in collaboration with the department, county juvenile court administrators, managed care organizations, the department of children, youth, and families, and behavioral health administrative services organizations, shall establish procedures for coordination among field offices, juvenile rehabilitation institutions, and county juvenile courts that result in prompt reinstatement of eligibility and speedy eligibility determinations for youth who are likely to be eligible for medical assistance services upon release from confinement. Procedures developed under this subsection must address:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_515__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Mechanisms for receiving medical assistance services' applications on behalf of confined youth in anticipation of their release from confinement;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_515__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Expeditious review of applications filed by or on behalf of confined youth and, to the extent practicable, completion of the review before the youth is released; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_09_515__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Mechanisms for providing medical assistance services' identity cards to youth eligible for medical assistance services immediately upon their release from confinement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_515__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For purposes of this section, &quot;confined&quot; or &quot;confinement&quot; means detained in a juvenile rehabilitation facility operated by or under contract with the department of children, youth, and families, or detained in a juvenile detention facility operated under chapter
13.04
RCW.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_09_515__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority shall adopt standardized statewide screening and application practices and forms designed to facilitate the application of a confined youth who is likely to be eligible for a medical assistance program.
[
2019 c 325 s 4003
;
2014 c 225 s 100
;
2011 1st sp.s. c 15 s 26
;
2007 c 359 s 8
.]
NOTES:
Effective date
—
2019 c 325:
See note following RCW
71.24.011
.
Effective date
—
2014 c 225:
See note following RCW
71.24.016
.
Effective date
—
Findings
—
Intent
—
Report
—
Agency transfer
—
References to head of health care authority
—
Draft legislation
—
2011 1st sp.s. c 15:
See notes following RCW
74.09.010
.
Captions not law
—
2007 c 359:
See note following RCW
71.36.005
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
