<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.010"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.010"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.010/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.010/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.010/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.010/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_60_010">
        <num>RCW 74.60.010</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Authority&quot; means the health care authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Base year&quot; for medicaid fee-for-service payments for state fiscal year 2024 is state fiscal year 2021. For each following year's calculations, the base year must be updated to the next following year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Border hospital&quot; means, for the purposes of the fee-for-service program under RCW
74.60.120
, a hospital as defined in WAC 182-550-1050 and bordering cities as described in WAC 182-501-0175, or successor rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Cancer hospital&quot; means a hospital classified as involved extensively in treatment for or research on cancer under section 1886</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_4__subsec_v">
            <num>(v)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of the social security act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Children's hospital&quot; means a hospital primarily serving children, as defined in WAC 182-550-1050 or successor rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Critical access hospital&quot; means a hospital as described in RCW
74.09.5225
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Designated public hospital&quot; means a hospital operated by a public hospital district in the state of Washington, not certified by the department of health as a critical access hospital, that:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Has not opted out of the certified public expenditure payment program described in WAC 182-550-4650 or successor rule by June 1, 2023, or in future years by June 1st of the preceding year; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Is an affiliate of a system of state and county-owned hospitals and is not participating in that system's intergovernmental transfer directed payment program as of June 1, 2023, or in future years by June 1st of the preceding calendar year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Director&quot; means the director of the health care authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Fund&quot; means the hospital safety net assessment fund established under RCW
74.60.020
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;High government payer independent hospital&quot; means a prospective payment system hospital which is nonprofit, provides acute care to adults and children, is not governmentally owned or owned or operated by a health system that owns or operates three or more acute care hospitals, and provides services to patients covered by medicare, medicaid, or other governmental payers as well as the uninsured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Hospital&quot; means a facility licensed under chapter
70.41
RCW.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Inflation factor&quot; means the centers for medicare and medicaid services inpatient hospital market basket inflation factor using the four quarter rolling average as calculated and available by April 30th of each year or an alternative source required by the centers for medicare and medicaid services.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Long-term acute care hospital&quot; means a hospital which has an average inpatient length of stay of greater than twenty-five days as determined by the department of health.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Managed care organization&quot; means an organization having a certificate of authority or certificate of registration from the office of the insurance commissioner that contracts with the authority under a comprehensive risk contract to provide prepaid health care services to eligible clients under the authority's medicaid managed care programs, including the healthy options program.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Medicaid&quot; means the medical assistance program as established in Title XIX of the social security act and as administered in the state of Washington by the authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Medicaid managed care inpatient discharge&quot; means an inpatient discharge for a medicaid patient, excluding normal newborns, based upon the grouper methodology used by the authority, where the medicaid managed care organization was the primary payer of the patient claim.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Medicaid managed care outpatient payments&quot; means outpatient services provided to a medicaid patient where a medicaid managed care organization was the primary payer of the patient claim.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Medicaid prospective payment system hospital&quot; means a hospital reimbursed for inpatient and outpatient services provided to medicaid beneficiaries under the inpatient prospective payment system and the outpatient prospective payment system as defined in WAC 182-550-1050 or successor rule, excluding any designated public hospital, any state or county-owned hospital, or any hospital located outside of the state of Washington and in one of the bordering cities listed in WAC 182-501-0175 or successor rule, or any hospital owned or operated by a health maintenance organization as defined in RCW
48.46.020
. &quot;Medicaid prospective payment system&quot; refers solely to a reimbursement under the state medicaid program and has no bearing on or reference to a hospital's reimbursement classification under federal health care or other payment programs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_19">
          <num>(19)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Medicare cost report&quot; means the medicare cost report, form 2552, or successor document.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_20">
          <num>(20)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Nonmedicare net patient revenue&quot; means all net patient revenue, less a deduction only of fee-for-service medicare revenue and includes medicare managed care revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_21">
          <num>(21)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Outpatient services&quot; means services that are provided as ambulatory payment classification services or successor payment methodologies as defined in WAC 182-550-1050 or successor rule and applies to fee-for-service payments and managed care encounter data.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_22">
          <num>(22)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;*Psychiatric hospital&quot; means a hospital facility licensed as a *psychiatric hospital under chapter
71.12
RCW.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_23">
          <num>(23)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Rehabilitation hospital&quot; means a medicare-certified freestanding inpatient rehabilitation facility.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_24">
          <num>(24)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Small rural disproportionate share hospital payment&quot; means a payment made in accordance with WAC 182-550-5200 or successor rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_25">
          <num>(25)</num>
          <content>
            <p>&quot;Upper payment limit&quot; means the aggregate federal upper payment limit on the amount of the medicaid payment for which federal financial participation is available for a class of service and a class of health care providers, as specified in 42 C.F.R. Part 47, as separately determined for inpatient and outpatient hospital services.
[
2023 c 430 s 2
;
2019 c 318 s 2
;
2017 c 228 s 2
;
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17 s 2
;
2010 1st sp.s. c 30 s 2
.]
NOTES:
Reviser's note:
*</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term &quot;psychiatric hospital&quot; was changed to &quot;behavioral health hospital&quot; by
2024 c 121 s 19
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_010__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The definitions in this section have been alphabetized pursuant to RCW
1.08.015</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
