<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.005"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.005"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.005/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.005/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.005/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.60.005/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_60_005">
        <num>RCW 74.60.005</num>
        <heading>Purpose—Findings—Intent</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The purpose of this chapter is to establish a safety net program, including an assessment on certain nongovernmental medicaid prospective payment system hospitals and critical access hospitals and an allowance for intergovernmental transfers for designated public hospitals, which will be used solely as specified in this chapter to maintain and improve equity of access to and quality of care of hospital services for medicaid clients, including those served by managed care organizations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The legislature finds that the program established by this chapter will allow the state to more fully realize the benefits of increased federal financial participation in the medicaid program and to address expanded medicaid enrollment resulting from federal health care reform, thereby benefiting medicaid clients.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In adopting this chapter, it is the intent of the legislature:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To condition the assessment as specified in RCW
74.60.150
, including:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Receipt and continuation of federal approval for payment of additional federal financial participation to support the payments provided for in RCW
74.60.100
through
74.60.130
; and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>continuation of funding from the state general fund sufficient to maintain aggregate payment levels to hospitals for inpatient and outpatient services covered by medicaid, including fee-for-service and managed care, at least at the rates the state paid for those services on July 1, 2022, as adjusted for current enrollment and utilization;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>That funds generated by the assessment will be matched with federal dollars whenever possible to achieve the maximum level of benefits, and that the total amount assessed under this chapter not exceed the amount needed, in combination with all other available funds, to support the payments authorized by this chapter;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>That upon satisfaction of the applicable conditions in RCW
74.60.090
, the designated public hospitals will be able to receive additional federal matching funds, used only for the purposes specified in this chapter.
[
2023 c 430 s 1
;
2021 c 255 s 1
;
2019 c 318 s 1
;
2017 c 228 s 1
;
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5 s 1
;
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17 s 1
;
2010 1st sp.s. c 30 s 1
.]
NOTES:
Contingent effective date
—
2023 c 430:
&quot;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Sections 1 through 7 and 9 through 16 of this act take effect when the conditions specified in RCW
74.60.150</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>are satisfied, but no earlier than January 1, 2024.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Section 8 of this act takes effect when the conditions specified in that section are satisfied, but no earlier than January 1, 2024.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Until the provisions of this act become effective, chapter
74.60
RCW remains in effect, provided that:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Failure to satisfy the conditions specified in section 8 of this act shall not prevent the remainder of this act taking effect; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In all events, payments under RCW
74.60.090</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall cease December 31, 2023.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority shall provide written notice of the effective date of each occurrence in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section to affected parties, the chief clerk of the house of representatives, the secretary of the senate, the office of the code reviser, and others as deemed appropriate by the authority.&quot; [
2023 c 430 s 18
.] The health care authority has notified the code reviser's office that the conditions specified in RCW
74.60.150</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_60_005__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and 2023 c 430 s 8 have been satisfied effective January 1, 2024.
Effective date
—
2019 c 318:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 2019.&quot; [
2019 c 318 s 9
.]
Effective date
—
2017 c 228:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect July 1, 2017.&quot; [
2017 c 228 s 15
.]
Effective date
—
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect immediately [June 30, 2015].&quot; [
2015 2nd sp.s. c 5 s 12
.]
Effective date
—
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing public institutions, and takes effect immediately [June 30, 2013].&quot; [
2013 2nd sp.s. c 17 s 20
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
