<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.465"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.465"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.465/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.465/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.465/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.14.465/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_14_465">
        <num>RCW 82.14.465</num>
        <heading>Hospital benefit zones—Sales and use tax—Definitions</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A city, town, or county that creates a benefit zone and finances public improvements pursuant to chapter
39.100
RCW may impose a sales and use tax in accordance with the terms of this chapter and subject to the criteria set forth in this section. Except as provided in this section, the tax is in addition to other taxes authorized by law and must be collected from those persons who are taxable by the state under chapters
82.08
and
82.12
RCW upon the occurrence of any taxable event within the taxing jurisdiction of the city, town, or county. The rate of tax may not exceed the rate provided in RCW
82.08.020</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>in the case of a sales tax or a use tax, less the aggregate rates of any other taxes imposed on the same events that are credited against the state taxes imposed under chapters
82.08
and
82.12
RCW. The tax rate may be no higher than what is reasonably necessary for the local government to receive its entire annual state contribution in a ten-month period of time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The tax imposed under subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section must be deducted from the amount of tax otherwise required to be collected or paid over to the department under chapter
82.08
or
82.12
RCW. The department must perform the collection of such taxes on behalf of the city, town, or county at no cost to the city, town, or county.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No tax may be imposed under this section before July 1, 2007. Before imposing a tax under this section, the city, town, or county shall first have received tax allocation revenues during the preceding calendar year. The tax imposed under this section expires on the earlier of the date:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax allocation revenues are no longer used for public improvements and public improvement costs;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the bonds issued to finance or refinance the improvements are no longer outstanding, if the bonds are issued; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_3__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that is thirty years after the tax is first imposed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An ordinance adopted by the legislative authority of a city, town, or county imposing a tax under this section must provide that:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax is first imposed on the first day of a fiscal year;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount of tax received by the local government in any fiscal year may not exceed the amount of the state contribution;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax must cease to be distributed for the remainder of any fiscal year in which either:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount of tax distributions totals the amount of the state contribution;</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of tax distributions totals the amount of local public sources, dedicated in the previous calendar year to finance public improvements authorized under chapter
39.100
RCW, expended in the previous year for public improvement costs, or used to pay for other bonds issued to pay for public improvements. Revenues from local public sources, including hospital sources identified in RCW
82.14.465</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_i__subsec_iii">
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of revenue from taxes imposed under this section by all cities, towns, and counties totals the annual state credit limit as provided in RCW
82.32.700</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tax must be distributed again, should it cease to be distributed for any of the reasons provided in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, at the beginning of the next fiscal year, subject to the restrictions in this section; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any revenue generated by the tax in excess of the amounts specified in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_4__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection belong to the state of Washington.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If both a county and a city or town impose a tax under this section, the tax imposed by the city, town, or county is credited as follows:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_5__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the county has created a benefit zone before the city or town, the tax imposed by the county is credited against the tax imposed by the city or town, the purpose of such credit is to give priority to the county tax; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_5__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the city or town has created a benefit zone before the county, the tax imposed by the city or town is credited against the tax imposed by the county, the purpose of such credit is to give priority to the city or town tax.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department must determine the amount of tax distributions attributable to each city, town, and county imposing a sales and use tax under this section and must advise a city, town, or county when the tax will cease to be distributed for the remainder of the fiscal year as provided in subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_6__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. Determinations by the department of the amount of taxes attributable to a city, town, or county are final and may not be used to challenge the validity of any tax imposed under this section. The department must remit any tax revenues in excess of the amounts specified in subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_6__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_6__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section to the state treasurer who must deposit the moneys in the general fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The definitions in this subsection apply throughout this section and RCW
82.14.470
unless the context clearly requires otherwise.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Base year&quot; means the calendar year immediately following the creation of a benefit zone.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Benefit zone&quot; has the same meaning as provided in RCW
39.100.010
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Excess local excise taxes&quot; has the same meaning as provided in RCW
39.100.050
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Excess state excise taxes&quot; means the amount of excise taxes received by the state during the measurement year from taxable activity within the benefit zone over and above the amount of excise taxes received by the state during the base year from taxable activity within the benefit zone. However, if a local government creates the benefit zone and reasonably determines that no activity subject to tax under chapters
82.08
and
82.12
RCW occurred in the twelve months immediately preceding the creation of the benefit zone within the boundaries of the area that became the benefit zone, &quot;excess state excise taxes&quot; means the entire amount of state excise taxes the state receives during a calendar year period beginning with the calendar year immediately following the creation of the benefit zone and continuing with each measurement year thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;State excise taxes&quot; means revenues derived from state retail sales and use taxes under chapters
82.08
and
82.12
RCW, less the amount of tax distributions from all local retail sales and use taxes imposed on the same taxable events that are credited against the state retail sales and use taxes under chapters
82.08
and
82.12
RCW except for the local tax authorized in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_f">
            <num>(f)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Fiscal year&quot; has the same meaning as provided in RCW
39.100.030
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_g">
            <num>(g)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Measurement year&quot; means a calendar year, beginning with the calendar year following the base year and each calendar year thereafter, that is used annually to measure the amount of excess state excise taxes and excess local excise taxes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_h">
            <num>(h)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;State contribution&quot; means the lesser of two million dollars or an amount equal to excess state excise taxes received by the state during the preceding calendar year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Tax allocation revenues&quot; has the same meaning as provided in RCW
39.100.010
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_j">
            <num>(j)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Public improvements&quot; and &quot;public improvement costs&quot; have the same meanings as provided in RCW
39.100.010
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_14_465__subsec_7__subsec_k">
            <num>(k)</num>
            <content>
              <p>&quot;Local public sources&quot; includes, but is not limited to, private monetary contributions, assessments, dedicated local government funds, and tax allocation revenues. &quot;Local public sources&quot; does not include local government funds derived from the state-subsidized portion of any state loan or state grant, any local tax that is credited against the state sales and use taxes, or any other state funds. Local public sources may include amounts expended by a hospital in the zone since the date of formation of the zone and may be applied to the year or years designated by the local government.
[
2011 c 363 s 3
;
2009 c 535 s 1109
;
2007 c 266 s 7
;
2006 c 111 s 7
.]
NOTES:
Intent
—
Construction
—
2009 c 535:
See notes following RCW
82.04.192
.
Finding
—
Application
—
Effective date
—
2007 c 266:
See notes following RCW
39.100.010
.
Effective date
—
2006 c 111:
See RCW
39.100.900
.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
