<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.080"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.080"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.080/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.080/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.080/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.080/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_39A_080">
        <num>RCW 74.39A.080</num>
        <heading>Department authority to take actions in response to noncompliance or violations</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department is authorized to take one or more of the actions listed in subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section in any case in which the department finds that a provider of assisted living services, adult residential care services, or enhanced adult residential care services has:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Failed or refused to comply with the requirements of this chapter or the rules adopted under this chapter;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Operated without a license or under a revoked license;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Knowingly, or with reason to know, made a false statement of material fact on his or her application for license or any data attached thereto, or in any matter under investigation by the department; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_2__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Willfully prevented or interfered with any inspection or investigation by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When authorized by subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, the department may take one or more of the following actions:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Refuse to issue a contract;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Impose reasonable conditions on a contract, such as correction within a specified time, training, and limits on the type of clients the provider may admit or serve;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Impose civil penalties of not more than one hundred dollars per day per violation;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_1__subsec_d">
            <num>(d)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Suspend, revoke, or refuse to renew a contract; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_1__subsec_e">
            <num>(e)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Suspend admissions to the facility by imposing stop placement on contracted services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the department orders stop placement, the facility shall not admit any person admitted by contract until the stop placement order is terminated. The department may approve readmission of a resident to the facility from a hospital or nursing home during the stop placement. The department shall terminate the stop placement when:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_3__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The violations necessitating the stop placement have been corrected; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the provider exhibits the capacity to maintain correction of the violations previously found deficient. However, if upon the revisit the department finds new violations that the department reasonably believes will result in a new stop placement, the previous stop placement shall remain in effect until the new stop placement is imposed.
After a department finding of a violation for which a stop placement has been imposed, the department shall make an on-site revisit of the provider within fifteen working days from the request for revisit, to ensure correction of the violation. For violations that are serious or recurring or uncorrected following a previous citation, and create actual or threatened harm to one or more residents' well-being, including violations of residents' rights, the department shall make an on-site revisit as soon as appropriate to ensure correction of the violation. Verification of correction of all other violations may be made by either a department on-site revisit or by written or photographic documentation found by the department to be credible. This subsection does not prevent the department from enforcing license suspensions or revocations. Nothing in this subsection shall interfere with or diminish the department's authority and duty to ensure that the provider adequately cares for residents, including to make departmental on-site revisits as needed to ensure that the provider protects residents, and to enforce compliance with this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_080__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Chapter
34.05
RCW applies to department actions under this section, except that orders of the department imposing contracts suspension, stop placement, or conditions for continuation of a contract are effective immediately upon notice and shall continue pending any hearing.
[
2001 c 193 s 3
;
1996 c 193 s 1
;
1995 1st sp.s. c 18 s 17
.]
NOTES:
Conflict with federal requirements
—
Severability
—
Effective date
—
1995 1st sp.s. c 18:
See notes following RCW
74.39A.030
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
