<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.170"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.170"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.170/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.170/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.170/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.170/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_39A_170">
        <num>RCW 74.39A.170</num>
        <heading>Recovery of payments—Transfer of assets rules for eligibility—Disclosure of estate recovery costs, terms, and conditions</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_170__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All payments made in state-funded long-term care shall be recoverable as if they were medical assistance payments subject to recovery under 42 U.S.C. Sec. 1396p and chapter
43.20B
RCW, but without regard to the recipient's age.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_170__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In determining eligibility for state-funded long-term care services programs, the department shall impose the same rules with respect to the transfer of assets for less than fair market value as are imposed under 42 U.S.C. 1396p with respect to nursing home and home and community services.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_170__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is the responsibility of the department to fully disclose in advance verbally and in writing, in easy to understand language, the terms and conditions of estate recovery to all persons offered long-term care services subject to recovery of payments.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_170__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In disclosing estate recovery costs to potential clients, and to family members at the consent of the client, the department shall provide a written description of the community service options.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_170__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department of social and health services shall develop an implementation plan for notifying the client or his or her legal representative at least quarterly of the types of services used and the cost of those services (debt) that will be charged against the estate. The estate planning implementation plan shall be submitted by December 12, 1999, to the appropriate standing committees of the house of representatives and the senate, and to the joint legislative and executive task force on long-term care.
[
1999 c 354 s 1
;
1995 1st sp.s. c 18 s 56
.]
NOTES:
Conflict with federal requirements
—
Severability
—
Effective date
—
1995 1st sp.s. c 18:
See notes following RCW
74.39A.030
.
Recovery for state-funded long-term care
—
Legislative intent: RCW
43.20B.090
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
