<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.035"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.035"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.035/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.035/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.035/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.39A.035/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_39A_035">
        <num>RCW 74.39A.035</num>
        <heading>Expansion of nutrition services through the meals on wheels program</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the availability of amounts appropriated for this specific purpose, the department of social and health services must develop a program to expand nutrition services through the meals on wheels program.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At least sixty-five percent of the moneys may be distributed according to formulae to existing providers of meals on wheels programs to expand the number of people served.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Up to twenty-five percent of the moneys may be distributed by a competitive grant process to expand the meals on wheels program into areas not presently being served.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_1__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Up to five percent of the moneys may be used by the department administration, monitoring of the grants, and providing technical assistance to existing and new meals on wheels providers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The department must develop criteria for awarding grants under subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section. The criteria must include, but is not limited to:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Expanding service in areas with the greatest need to assist low-income homebound seniors who are unable to prepare food for themselves and lack a caregiver that prepares meals;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Expanding services in areas where senior citizens have limited access to community support services and facilities; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_2__subsec_c">
            <num>(c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Geographic diversity within the state and between rural and urban areas.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>None of the grant moneys awarded under subsection</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_3__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section may be used to supplant existing funds the provider receives for the meals on wheels program.
[
2017 c 287 s 2
.]
NOTES:
Findings
—
2017 c 287:
&quot;The legislature finds that:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Washingtonians sixty-five years of age and older will nearly double in the next twenty-five years, from twelve percent of our population in 2015 to almost twenty-two percent of our population in 2040. Younger people with disabilities will also require supportive long-term care services.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The long-term care system should support autonomy and self-determination. Furthermore, the long-term care system should promote personal planning and savings combined with public support, when needed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever possible, the long-term care system should utilize evidence-based practices to improve the general health of Washingtonians over their lifetime[s] and reduce related health care and long-term care costs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_39A_035__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nutrition programs, such as the meals on wheels program, are a low-cost method of helping seniors remain independent.&quot; [
2017 c 287 s 1
.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
