<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.130"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.130"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.130/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.130/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.130/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/82.16.130/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_82_16_130">
        <num>RCW 82.16.130</num>
        <heading>Renewable energy system cost recovery—Light/power business tax credit. (Expires June 30, 2033.)</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A light and power business is allowed a credit against taxes due under this chapter in an amount equal to:</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_1__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Incentive payments made in any fiscal year under RCW
82.16.120
and
82.16.165
; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_1__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any fees a utility is allowed to recover pursuant to RCW
82.16.165</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The credits must be taken in a form and manner as required by the department. The credit taken under this section for the fiscal year may not exceed one and one-half percent of the business's taxable Washington power sales generated in calendar year 2014 and due under RCW
82.16.020</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or two hundred fifty thousand dollars, whichever is greater, for incentive payments made for the following:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_2__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Renewable energy systems, other than community solar projects, that are certified for an incentive payment as of June 30, 2020; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Community solar and shared commercial projects that are under precertification status under RCW
82.16.165</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_2__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>as of June 30, 2020, and that are certified for an incentive payment in accordance with the terms of that precertification by June 30, 2022.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The credit may not exceed the tax that would otherwise be due under this chapter. Refunds may not be granted in the place of credits. Expenditures not used to earn a credit in one fiscal year may not be used to earn a credit in subsequent years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For any business that has claimed credit for amounts that exceed the correct amount of the incentive payable under RCW
82.16.120
, the amount of tax against which credit was claimed for the excess payments is immediately due and payable. The department may deduct amounts due from future credits claimed by the business.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_4__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as provided in</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this subsection, the department must assess interest but not penalties on the taxes against which the credit was claimed. Interest must be assessed at the rate provided for delinquent excise taxes under chapter
82.32
RCW, retroactively to the date the credit was claimed, and accrues until the taxes against which the credit was claimed are repaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_4__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A business is not liable for excess payments made in reliance on amounts reported by the Washington State University extension energy program as due and payable as provided under RCW
82.16.165</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of credit taken under this section is not confidential taxpayer information under RCW
82.32.330
and is subject to disclosure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The right to earn tax credits for incentive payments made under RCW
82.16.120
expires June 30, 2020. Credits may not be claimed after June 30, 2021.</p>
          </content>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_6__subsec_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The right to earn tax credits for incentive payments made under RCW
82.16.165
for the following expires June 30, 2029:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_6__subsec_i">
            <num>(i)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Renewable energy systems, other than community solar projects, that are certified for an incentive payment as of June 30, 2020; and</p>
            </content>
            <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_6__subsec_i__subsec_ii">
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Community solar and shared commercial projects that are under precertification status under RCW
82.16.165</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_6__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>as of June 30, 2020, and that are certified for an incentive payment in accordance with the terms of that precertification by June 30, 2022.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_6__subsec_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Credits may not be claimed after June 30, 2030.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_82_16_130__subsec_8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section expires June 30, 2033.
[
2022 c 212 s 2
;
2017 3rd sp.s. c 36 s 4
;
2010 c 202 s 3
;
2009 c 469 s 506
;
2005 c 300 s 4
.]
NOTES:
Findings
—
Intent
—
Tax preference performance statement exemption
—
Effective date
—
2022 c 212:
See notes following RCW
82.16.183
.
Finding
—
Intent
—
2017 3rd sp.s. c 36:
&quot;The legislature finds and declares that stimulating local investment in distributed renewable energy generation is an important part of a state energy strategy, helping to increase energy independence from fossil fuels, promote economic development, hedge against the effects of climate change, and attain environmental benefits. The legislature intends to increase the effectiveness of the existing renewable energy investment cost recovery program by reducing the maximum incentive rate provided for each kilowatt-hour of electricity generated by a renewable energy system over the period of the program and by creating opportunities for broader participation by low-income individuals and others who may not own the premises where a renewable energy system may be installed. The legislature intends to provide an incentive sufficient to promote installation of systems through 2021, at which point the legislature expects that the state's renewable energy industry will be capable of sustained growth and vitality without the cost recovery incentive. The legislature intends for the program to balance the deployment of community solar and shared commercial solar projects in order to support participation in renewable energy generation, and that deployment of community solar projects is balanced among eligible utilities, nonprofits, and local housing authorities, as doing so will support maximum deployment of renewable energy generation throughout the state.&quot; [
2017 3rd sp.s. c 36 s 1
.]
Effective date
—
2017 3rd sp.s. c 36:
&quot;This act is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety, or support of the state government and its existing p</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
