<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13.515"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13.515"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13.515/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13.515/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13.515/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13.515/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_13_515">
        <num>RCW 74.13.515</num>
        <heading>Disclosure of child welfare records—Fatalities</heading>
        <content>
          <p>Print
RCWs
&gt;
Title 74
&gt;
Chapter 74.13
&gt;
Section 74.13.515
74.13.510
&lt;&lt; 
        74.13.515 &gt;&gt;
74.13.520
PDF
RCW
74.13.515
Disclosure of child welfare records
—
Fatalities.
For purposes of RCW
74.13.500
(1)(d), the secretary must make the fullest possible disclosure consistent with chapter
42.56
RCW and applicable federal law in cases of all fatalities of children who were in the care of, or receiving services from, the department at the time of their death or within the twelve months previous to their death.
If the secretary specifically determines that disclosure of the name of the deceased child is contrary to the best interests of the child's siblings or other children in the household, the secretary may remove personally identifying information.
For the purposes of this section, &quot;personally identifying information&quot; means the name, street address, social security number, and day of birth of the child who died and of private persons who are relatives of the child named in child welfare records. &quot;Personally identifying information&quot; shall not include the month or year of birth of the child who has died. Once this personally identifying information is removed, the remainder of the records pertaining to a child who has died must be released regardless of whether the remaining facts in the records are embarrassing to the unidentifiable other private parties or to identifiable public workers who handled the case.
[
2018 c 284 s 56
;
2009 c 520 s 85
;
2005 c 274 s 352
;
1997 c 305 s 5
.]
NOTES:
Conflict with federal requirements
—
1997 c 305:
See note following RCW
74.13.500
.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
