<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.050"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.050"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.050/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.050/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.050/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.13A.050/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_13A_050">
        <num>RCW 74.13A.050</num>
        <heading>Agreements as contracts within state and federal Constitutions—State's continuing obligation</heading>
        <content>
          <p>Print
RCWs
&gt;
Title 74
&gt;
Chapter 74.13A
&gt;
Section 74.13A.050
74.13A.047
&lt;&lt; 
        74.13A.050 &gt;&gt;
74.13A.055
PDF
RCW
74.13A.050
Agreements as contracts within state and federal Constitutions
—
State's continuing obligation.
An agreement for adoption support made before January 1, 1985, or pursuant to RCW
26.33.320
and
74.13A.005
through
74.13A.080
, although subject to review and adjustment as provided for herein, shall, as to the standard used by the secretary in making such review or reviews and any such adjustment, constitutes a contract within the meaning of section 10, Article I of the United States Constitution and section 23, Article I of the state Constitution. For that reason once such an agreement has been made any review of and adjustment under such agreement shall as to the standards used by the secretary, be made only subject to the provisions of RCW
26.33.320
and
74.13A.005
through
74.13A.080
and such rules and regulations relating thereto as they exist on the date of the initial determination in connection with such agreement or such more generous standard or parts of such standard as may hereafter be provided for by law or regulation. Once made such an agreement shall constitute a solemn undertaking by the state of Washington with such adoptive parent or parents. The termination of the effective period of RCW
26.33.320
and
74.13A.005
through
74.13A.080
or a decision by the state or federal government to discontinue or reduce general appropriations made available for the purposes to be served by RCW
26.33.320
and
74.13A.005
through
74.13A.080
, shall not affect the state's specific continuing obligations to support such adoptions, subject to such annual review and adjustment for all such agreements as have theretofore been entered into by the state.
The purpose of this section is to assure any such parent that, upon his or her consenting to assume the burdens of adopting a hard to place child, the state will not in future so act by way of general reduction of appropriations for the program authorized by RCW
26.33.320
and
74.13A.005
through
74.13A.080
or ratable reductions, to impair the trust and confidence necessarily reposed by such parent in the state as a condition of such parent taking upon himself or herself the obligations of parenthood of a difficult to place child.
Should the secretary and any such adoptive parent differ as to whether any standard or part of a standard adopted by the secretary after the date of an initial agreement, which standard or part is used by the secretary in making any review and adjustment, is more generous than the standard in effect as of the date of the initial determination with respect to such agreement such adoptive parent may invoke his or her rights, including all rights of appeal under the fair hearing provisions, available to him or her under RCW
74.13A.055
.
[
2009 c 520 s 67
;
1985 c 7 s 140
;
1971 ex.s. c 63 s 9
. Formerly RCW
74.13.124
.]</p>
        </content>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
