<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="section">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#wa-legislature">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.42.230"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.42.230"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enacted"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-wa"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.42.230/eng"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.42.230/eng"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#wa-legislature"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.42.230/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/us-wa/act/rcw/74.42.230/eng/akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#cosilico"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#cosilico">
        <TLCOrganization eId="wa-legislature" href="/ontology/organization/us-wa/legislature" showAs="Washington State Legislature"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <section eId="sec_74_42_230">
        <num>RCW 74.42.230</num>
        <heading>Physician or authorized practitioner to prescribe medication—Communication of order by licensed nurse, pharmacist, or another physician</heading>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_42_230__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The resident's attending or staff physician or authorized practitioner approved by the attending physician shall order all medications for the resident. The order may be oral or written and shall continue in effect until discontinued by a physician or other authorized prescriber, unless the order is specifically limited by time. An &quot;authorized practitioner,&quot; as used in this section, is a registered nurse under chapter
18.79
RCW when authorized by the state board of nursing, a physician assistant under chapter
18.71A
RCW when authorized by the Washington medical commission, or a pharmacist under chapter
18.64
RCW when authorized by the pharmacy quality assurance commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_42_230__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An oral order shall be given only to a licensed nurse, pharmacist, or another physician. The oral order shall be recorded and physically or electronically signed immediately by the person receiving the order. The attending physician shall sign the record of the oral order in a manner consistent with good medical practice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_42_230__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A licensed nurse, pharmacist, or another physician receiving and recording an oral order may, if so authorized by the physician or authorized practitioner, communicate that order to a pharmacy on behalf of the physician or authorized practitioner. The order may be communicated verbally by telephone, by facsimile manually signed by the person receiving the order pursuant to subsection</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection eId="sec_74_42_230__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of this section, or by electronic transmission pursuant to RCW
69.41.055
. The communication of a resident's order to a pharmacy by a licensed nurse, pharmacist, or another physician acting at the prescriber's direction has the same force and effect as if communicated directly by the delegating physician or authorized practitioner. Nothing in this provision limits the authority of a licensed nurse, pharmacist, or physician to delegate to an authorized agent, including but not limited to delegation of operation of a facsimile machine by credentialed facility staff, to the extent consistent with his or her professional license.
[
2025 c 58 s 5057
;
2020 c 80 s 57
;
2019 c 55 s 20
;
2016 c 148 s 9
;
1994 sp.s. c 9 s 751
;
1982 c 120 s 2
;
1979 ex.s. c 211 s 23
.]
NOTES:
Explanatory note
—
2025 c 58:
See note following RCW
1.16.050
.
Effective date
—
2020 c 80 ss 12-59:
See note following RCW
7.68.030
.
Intent
—
2020 c 80:
See note following RCW
18.71A.010
.
Severability
—
Headings and captions not law
—
Effective date
—
1994 sp.s. c 9:
See RCW
18.79.900
through
18.79.902
.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
